<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some remarques upon a late popular piece of nonsence called Julian the apostate, &amp;c. together, with a particular vindication of His Royal Highness the Duke of York, by some bold truths in answer to a great many impudent calumnies raised against him, by the foolish arguments, false reasonings and suppositions, imposed upon the publick from several scandalous and seditious pamphlets especially from one more notorious and generally virulent than the rest, sometime since published under the title of A Tory Plot, &amp;c. / by a lover of truth, vertue, and justice.</title>
            <author>Meredith, Edward, 1648-1689?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 216 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23540</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12767306</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12767306</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93598</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50646)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93598)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 698:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some remarques upon a late popular piece of nonsence called Julian the apostate, &amp;c. together, with a particular vindication of His Royal Highness the Duke of York, by some bold truths in answer to a great many impudent calumnies raised against him, by the foolish arguments, false reasonings and suppositions, imposed upon the publick from several scandalous and seditious pamphlets especially from one more notorious and generally virulent than the rest, sometime since published under the title of A Tory Plot, &amp;c. / by a lover of truth, vertue, and justice.</title>
                  <author>Meredith, Edward, 1648-1689?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 35, 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Davies,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Philanax Misopapas. --  Tory plot.</term>
               <term>Johnson, Samuel, 1649-1703. --  Julian the Apostate.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:93598:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
SOME REMARQUES Upon a late Popular Piece of Nonſence CALLED Julian the Apoſtate, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With a Particular VINDICATION OF HIS Royal Highneſs THE DUKE of YORK.</p>
            <p>By ſome Bold TRUTHS in Anſwer to a great many Impudent Calumnies raiſed againſt HIM, by the Fooliſh Arguments, Falſe Reaſonings and Suppoſitions, impoſed upon the Publick from ſeveral Scandalous and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Pamphlets; Eſpecially from one more Notorious and generally Virulent than the reſt, ſometime ſince Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed under the Title of <hi>A TORY PLOT,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of <hi>Truth, Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Si fractus Illabatur Orbis</l>
                  <l>Impa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idum ferient Ruinae:</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>Horat. Lib. 3. Ode 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Davies,</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93598:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93598:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe Pamphlet called <hi>A Tory Plot,</hi> coming ſometime ſince to my Hands when I was far diſtant from <hi>London,</hi> and at a Quiet Retirement, did very much ſurprize me; and gave me in the midſt of my dear Shades and Meadows, often very Melancholy wayward Thoughts. When I read the Matter it contained, Conſidered the End it aimed it, and reflected on what ſort of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture might probably be the Author of it; I could not forbear Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning in my ſelf the Vice I know not ſometimes how to get rid of, called Ambition: for when I reflected that half a ſcore ſheets of Paper, ſo weakly furniſhed as I found that Trifle to be, carry'd popular force enough to ſhake the Affections of a People towards a Prince, whom they Owe ſo much to as this Thankleſs Nation does to the Heroick Vertue, Valour, and Sufferings of His Royal Highneſs; I could not but in ſome meaſure prize my own poor Condition, which Fate had placed too low to be worth the Malice of Knaves, and yet in a happineſs too finely wrapt up, and couched for the Envy of Fools to find it. I waited much, and expected long an Anſwer to a Libel, which Reflected ſo notoriouſly as that did upon the Government, and ſtruck ſo impudently at the very being of it. I thought it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that in ſo glorious a Metropolis as that of <hi>London,</hi> the Center of all the Arts and Learning of this flouriſhing Kingdom; ſo Good and Gracious a King, as our preſent Juſt and Merciful Sovereign; ſo Gallant a Prince, ſo Unfailing a Friend, and ſo Kind a Maſter as his Generous Brother; could ever want Servants, able and ready to take in hand ſo glorious a Cauſe, and not ſuffer ſo lewd and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced an Affront as that, to the Dignity and Prerogatives of the Crown, as well as the Rights of the Royal Family, to go uncorrected: I thought all this, but I was much deceived: In juſt Indignation then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Ingratitude or Ignorance of Unprofitable Servants, and in honour
<pb facs="tcp:93598:3"/>
to the Authority and Character of that Glorious Monarch, whom it is my greateſt Pride that I was born to live a Subject under: I thought it my Duty as an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> and an Honeſt man, to exert what little Abitities I have (if I have any at all) to do his Cauſe (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he is perſonally or relatively concerned in that ſawcy Libel) the Juſtice it deſerves. I was aſhamed to think that Men who live by the Service and Favour of a Prince, and whoſe Well-being does, or ought to depend entirely upon his; ſhould, when their Bellies are fill'd every day with his Bread, and their Purſes with his Bounty, lay their hands upon their Mouths, or keep them in their Pockets, and neither ſay or do any thing for his Vindication and Service; but are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther apt to cringe, and bend the Knee to the moſt inſolent of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and when they falſly tell him they are his Friends, whiſper it in his Ear, for fear ſome Acquaintance ſpy whom they know to be in the Train, ſhould hear it. Of this ſort are thoſe, who come and bow at his riſing in the Morning, and then go to ſome Rebel Clubb, and tell the Secrets of the Bed-Chamber for a Dinner. Of this ſort are thoſe, who get Preferments, in the beſt and moſt profitable Offices of a Court, and employ the credit of their Maſter's Service againſt his Intereſt in the Country: And of this ſort are thoſe, that often divert a Princes Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements and Favour from his Friends, and when the ſtream of his Goodneſs is running the right way, turn it aſide from the Merit it was aimed at, to flow upon Tools like themſelves, whoſe Bribes have corrupted them; unable and unfit to be Employ'd, and too unfaithful to be Truſted.</p>
            <p>After having therefore vainly expected ſome Months an Anſwer to the above-mentioned Pamphlet; I took it in hand though late, moſt for my own Satisfaction, and in Complyance to the deſires of ſome private Friends, that often mourn with me for the Calamities of their afflicted Native Country. And after having finiſhed it, and pleaſed them (with ſomething they found in it) more than my ſelf; I lay'd it by, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it too late to make it Publick, in regard the Credit of the Paper it Corrected ſeemed to be blown over, and the noiſe of it utterly forgotten. Beſides being in hopes, by the daily Succeſs of the King's Affairs, that ſome lucid Intervals were coming to eaſe the Publick Madneſs: I thought it would not be proper to diſturb the tender Peace that was brooding over us, by ſtirring up anew the unruly Storm, that ſeemed at preſent to decline to ſome Calmneſs.</p>
            <p>But in the midſt of theſe ſoothing hopes, I was alarum'd afreſh with another guſt from the Old unquiet Corner; and that was the ſtinking blaſt of a Deacon, that had long been grip't and in pain with the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb facs="tcp:93598:3"/>
till out it came rattling with the Title of <hi>Julian the Apoſtate:</hi> I read it over, and lay'd it by, for the uſe I thought it only deſerved; 'till being accidentally one day at Court, for as little Bus neſs as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Forty more had there, who ſeemed nevertheleſs Fifty times buſier than I did; up comes me two meer Motions, with their Politick faces on, a little Worm wriggling behind them, impatient of an approaching Knighthood; near trim'd they were, and their ſhooes very clean; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date their Countenances, and ſoft their aſpect: till one of them of a ſudden (gathering his browes over his eyes) cry'd, <hi>How! Julian the Apoſtate!</hi> Ay, ſays his Companion (with the ſame dull Grimace) <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian the Apoſtate: A ſhrew'd Fellow, I'll warrant him! an unanſwerable Piece! Things as they ſtand will never do: Meaſures muſt be altered:</hi> Bleſs us, thought I, ſurely I am in a Trance! and this is one of <hi>Don Quevedo</hi>'s Viſions. Can this Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low be fit to ſerve in the Palace of a King? Adminiſter in Office to the Mighty Ruler of Three great Kingdoms, and talk at this wretched rate! So I bit my Lip, turn'd aſide, went home, entered my Cloſet; and taking Pen, Ink, and Paper, reſolved for once to convince a Politician (if by chance he can read) that the Author of <hi>Julian the Apoſtate</hi> is not ſo dreadful a Bugbear, but that a Man of Moderate gifts may anſwer him, without breaking his Brains, or falling into a Conſumption.</p>
            <p>And ſo having made the following Remarks upon it, and putting of them into ſuch ſtyle and order as I thought the Author and the Argument of his Work deſerved; it came into my Head that it would not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper (ſince it lay uſeleſs by me, and that his Royal Highneſs's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest and Honour were concerned in one as well as the other,) to Publiſh the following Vindication of that Prince, which I had written before, in Anſwer to the <hi>Tory Plot,</hi> with this Chaſtiſement of an Apoſtate Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, the Author of <hi>Julian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I rather choſe to call the Anſwer to the <hi>Tory Plot,</hi> A <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Royal Highneſs,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe I found in it, ſumm'd up all the Popular and moſt Current Arguments, that have paſſed with prejudiced or miſ-informed People to his diſadvantage: and if I have done him and his Cauſe any Juſtice, I have my end and reward in it; if I have not, I am ſure he is ſo good and gracious a Prince to forgive my failings, and accept of my good wiſhes, however ineffectual may prove my Endeavours.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible I ſhall undergo many Cenſures bitter enough: But let thoſe that think hardly of me for this, firſt Conſider, That I write according to my Conſcience: and hope that thoſe who contend ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:93598:4"/>
for Liberty of Conſcience themſelves, will not be ſcandalized at the freedom of mine.</p>
            <p>But what will they ſay? May be they will ſay I hope for a Penſion; with all my Soul: I ſhould be glad if I had one; or may be they will ſay, that I look for other Preferment: If they do, they may be in the right ſtill, but may be I am in the wrong; for when I ſee ſometimes how Matters go, and who are in my way, were I to write for Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at Court, for ought I know, I have not taken the right ſide. In a word, as <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid when he was mealy-mouthed, and did not think fitting to explain himſelf to ſome impertinent Critical Jews, that meant him no good by their Inquiſitiveneſs: <hi>What I have written I have written.</hi> All honeſt Men I am ſure will make the beſt of it, and let others make their moſt of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93598:4"/>
            <head>SOME REMARQUES Upon a late <hi>Popular Piece of Nonſence</hi> CALL'D Julian the Apoſtate, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAving taken the following Pamphlet of a <hi>Tory Plot</hi> in hand late for the Reaſons be forementioned in the Preface, no ſooner had I diſcomfited that Gyant, but up roſe another, and a terrible one, a man would think him indeed by his Title, <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate in the Devil's Name; Being a ſhort Account of his Life, the Senſe of the Primitive Chriſtians about his Succeſſion, and their Behaviour towards him; together with a Compariſon of Popery and Paganiſm. Bleſs us thought I! What will become of us now! Immediately upon Enquiry, finding him an Enemy, I began to examine how I might Attack him, when to terrifie me the more, I find him intrenched within a Preface Six or Eight and twenty Pages deep at leaſt: Now to break in upon this <hi>Goliah,</hi> overthrow his Bulwark, and make a Raſcal of him, would be an Exploit indeed. This I truſt may be done, and thus I begin with him.</p>
            <p>The Author of the abovementioned Treatiſe, 'tis reaſonably to be ſuppoſed would have the World believe that he has taken a great deal of pains to overthrow the Duke of <hi>Tork</hi>'s Right to Succeſſion; and that he has acquitted himſelf particularly in it, by expoſing a Figure of his own making, which he calls the Picture of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate; and ſetting it out with an Inſcription at the Bottom, which he ſtyles, <hi>A Parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Paganiſm, and Popery.</hi> An Inſcription, truly as much to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as Sir <hi>Patience Ward</hi>'s Narrative round the Monument: For as that poſitively Charges the Papiſts with the Firing of <hi>London</hi> in Sixty Six, when in the Original Inſcription on the Weſt ſide of it, the whole is Attributed to the Juſt Judgment of God for their Sins: So this Fellow pretends in the firſt Part of his Book, by Compariſon to throw as much Odium as his Ignorance is capable of, upon an Injured Suffering Prince,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93598:5"/>
by Pleading the Cauſe of Proteſtancy againſt Popery and Paganiſm, when the whole Tenure and Bulk of his Book is nothing elſe but an abſolute Panegyrick upon <hi>Julian,</hi> and an Apology for <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may at firſt, 'tis poſſible, ſeem ſomething ſtrange to the Reader that has not Peruſed the Book now under conſideration ſo cautiouſly as I have done; But to prove how much a Friend our Author is to Apoſtacy, be pleaſed to take him flying in the face of Truth, in this his very Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark of a Preface, where he charges many of our late Addreſſers for offering their Lives and Fortunes, and the laſt drop of their Blood in the Defence of His Majeſty, and the Religion now Eſtabliſhed by Law; and by and by promiſing the ſame over again to a Popiſh Succeſſor. This is flying in the face of Truth, and commonly known in ſpeech by the Name of a <hi>Lye;</hi> for if there be any ſuch thing as a Popiſh Succeſſor men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in one of thoſe Addreſſes he is ſo angry withal, I will renounce all Loyalty and Religion in the World, and be as true a Friend to Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy and Paganiſm, as our Author is.</p>
            <p>For he is indeed an Author of an extraordinary Cut, abounding in much popular Nonſence, fain would Scribble to perſwade, but it is not his Talent, has taken up abundance of Knotty pieces of Learning upon Truſt, by the help of Indexes, but wants Senſe and common Principles of Literature to diſtinguiſh and diſpoſe them to any purpoſe; Pretends to top a Generation of People upon us for Primitive Chriſtians, which there is not a Deacon in <hi>England</hi> but can tell him lived in a very latter Century corrupted by Arianiſm, and inſtead of the faithful Quotations of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which ought to have been his Proofs of Matter of fact ſo long ago Tranſacted, he foiſts upon us the outragious Rhetorick of particular Men's Invectives, that were angry for loſs of their Eccleſiaſtical Dignities. Would it not be a worthy Author hereafter that ſhould quote <hi>Hickeringell</hi> againſt Biſhops, if there once were Occaſion, and perſwade Poſterity to believe, that becauſe he flew in the face of his <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> that all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in <hi>England</hi> were by general conſent for throwing off Epiſcopacy; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that profligate Fellow took the opportunity of a Licentious Preſs to Publiſh his Invectives againſt the Reverend Fathers that found it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to cenſure and reſtrain the looſeneſs of his Manners, that ſo ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd his Character. But to return to our Preface.</p>
            <p>Says he, <hi>All the Sober Men that I have met with, who remain unſatisfy'd as to a Bill of Excluſion, do nevertheleſs acknowledge, that a Popiſh Succeſſor will be a heavy Judgment of God to this Nation, to which we muſt patiently ſubmit, as we do to all other Calamities:</hi> But in the name of Madneſs, what is all this to us? what have we to do with the noiſe and buz of <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> if our Author will needs Diſpute with us about the convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or inconveniency of one, let him firſt prove his Principle, let him firſt ſhew us his <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> and convince us demonſtratively (as in all Matters of Fact we ought to be) that he is One; and when that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed once, we are content to joyn iſſue with him; but in the mean time, though apprehending the worſt, let us at the utmoſt but Pray againſt it, not Rebel upon the pretence of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93598:5"/>
How fooliſhly a little farther has he thought himſelf very ſhrewd in citing the Example of a Man infected with the Plague? how <hi>they are impriſoned and put under a very cloſe Confinement when they have committed no Fault;</hi> This indeed, where an unhappy Man comes to be ſo Infected, ought to be done for the good of the Town or Village; But he is a very vile Chriſtian, That will give his Neighbour an ill Name, and ſcandalize him with a dangerous Diſeaſe, only on purpoſe to have his Houſe ſhut up, and a Mark ſet on him to make him odious to his fellow Citizens, when at Bottom, twenty to one, but he's an honeſter founder Man, and fairer Dealer than his Accuſer. And that this has been the foul Practice uſed againſt the Duke of <hi>Tork,</hi> no Man that reads our Author and his Brethren Pamphletteers of the ſame ſlamp, but may be ſufficiently ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd<hi>:</hi> How has he been Hunted and Halloo'd about the World by the cry of Villains roaring out againſt him, Popery, Plot, Subverſion of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when their very top Raſcal, the <hi>Salamanchite</hi> himſelf, ſwore upon his firſt Diſcovery, That his Highneſs knew nothing of the Matter, but if he could not be drawn over, was to ſuffer the ſame Fate with his Brother: Yet as Matters grew riper, and riper, Bills of Recuſancy were to be prefer'd againſt him, and the aforeſaid Villain could ſwear through a Key-hole that was never tranſparent. But how much greater Villains muſt they be that can baſely unſpirit themſelves to Rake in the foul Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Perjury, for dirt to throw continually upon the Innocence of a Prince that may be half of'em never ſaw, and I am ſure none of 'em were ever injur'd by. What a ſhame it is that every Proſſigate Rogue, whoſe ill manners, and leud life have made a Vagabond, ſhould be permitted with Impunity to arraign the Honour and precious Fame of a Prince that has Virtues enough to Attone for all the Sins of his Enemies; nay, and to do it nonſenſically too, fulſomly, dully; with hardly true <hi>English,</hi> and no manner of right reaſoning; this is a grievance intollerable. Let me, if I muſt be defamed, ſuffer by the Tongue or Pen of a Raſcal that has at leaſt ſome Common ſence, that may pleaſe me in ſome meaſure by his Wit, when he offers at my ruin with his Falſhood, let not my Reputation be choakt up with the foul, muddy defluxions of an undiſtinguiſhing crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed Blockhead's Brains that ſhall make me ſick with his Nonſence, and only that way diſable me from anſwering his Calumny.</p>
            <p>In ſhort as to our Author in hand, it is very palpable from his Book, that he is either according to vulgar Expreſſion, <hi>Very much a Knave, or very much a Fool;</hi> and truly upon conſidering his Writings, I cannot well judge which of thoſe qualities have the Predominancy, for they are both very Powerful in his works, the Records of his Virtues. But I intend fairly to give the World an account what I have obſerv'd of thoſe two Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies in him, and leave the Reader to judge which Title he has beſt pretence to.</p>
            <p>To proceed then, Would any but a Knave of the higheſt form, ſo far betray his Cauſe as to call thoſe <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> who lived as I mentioned before in a very latter Century, and had already the Hereſie of <hi>Arrianiſm</hi> crept in amongſt 'em? or as he has done afterwards, would boaſt of his Quotations, that he had <hi>not impoveriſh'd the Subject,</hi> when he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93598:6"/>
has falſly corrupted it, with Fictions of his own, and added ſuch ſilly Falſhoods as no honeſt Man durſt have done, and any Scholar would have ſcorn'd. This I ſhall prove in what's to follow.</p>
            <p>Again, Who, but as very a Knave would have wrote thus. <hi>I cannot own my belief of this as a firſt Principle, that the Laws of a Man's Countrey are the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of all Civil Obedience.</hi> I would fain be Informed (might I be ſo bold as to offer the Queſtion, what it is our Author would obey, if not the Laws of his Country? How vilely does he Cant afterwards upon the Interpretation of Paſſive Obedience, inſinuating as if it were ever taught without regards to Laws: for, there is no Obedience underſtood in the World, but what is Obedience to ſome Law or another, All Obedience is to Authority: But Power indeed and Authority may be abſtracted, and are in ſignification ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from each other, Power in it ſelf is deſpotick and unlimitable; but when Law is added to it, then it is ſoftned into Authority, and the yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it ſo qualify'd, we call Civil Obedience: but the yielding to the force of Power is not underſtood by the term of Obedience, but that of Submiſſion, and we only ſubmit when we no longer can reſiſt, but we obey when we no longer ought to do it; Paſſive Submiſſion is an Effect of Neceſſity, but Paſſive Obedience is the Effect of Duty. His example therefore of St. <hi>Paul</hi> is falſly inſtanced, where he ſays, he was not for Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience, in that he pleaded and ſtood upon his Birthright; for if it were his Birthright he ſtood upon, that was the Law, and by that Plea he refer'd and abſolutely threw himſelf upon the Law, which was as much Paſſive Obedience as the moſt Patient man could ſhew: 'Tis an endleſs Drudgery to anſwer the confuſed Cant of an ignorant miſchievous Fool, though we are bound to it in Charity to the Publick Tranquillity.</p>
            <p>Again, How fooliſhly has he taken the opportunity to tell us a Story of a Purſuivant, ſent illegally to Arreſt the Body of a Man to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judges of an Aſſize, which Purſuivant was killed in the Action; and ſays he, <hi>The Arreſt afterwards was adjudged</hi> Tortius, <hi>and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the killing of the Purſuivant proved afterwards no Murder:</hi> Now all I have to urge in anſwer to this is, Let my Friend Mr. <hi>Topham</hi> have a care hereafter how he ventures too boldly into the Countrey, to dragg up honeſt Gentlemen upon Arbitrary Votes, that have no Authority out of the houſe they are made in.</p>
            <p>What in the name of <hi>Nonſence</hi> does he mean by telling us in this place an Impertinent Story, <hi>how the Church of</hi> England <hi>divides her Reverence betwixt the Ancient Fathers, and the firſt Reformers of the Church?</hi> What, or who does he mean by thoſe firſt Reformers! I fear upon inquiring into the Hiſtory of our Reformation, (I mean, not that Written by a Noble Doctor that ſhall be Nameleſs: but) I mean, That excellent Hiſtory Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a Nobleman of Honour <hi>(viz.</hi> The Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Cherbury)</hi> we ſhall find the firſt Cauſes of our Reformation not ſo Religiouſly and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly grounded, how good ſoever the Effect proved, as it is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for us to believe they were: I love and adhere to the Reformation as it is Eſtabliſhed by Law withal my heart; but I hate an Ignorant Fellow ſhould with his ſlovenly Fingers once touch ſo pure, ſo nice, and ſo delicate a piece of Diſcipline and Goſpel Perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93598:6"/>
In the next place, let us examine to what purpoſe he recites to us the Example of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots, There are,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Worthies enough that were Excluders with a Witneſs.</hi> Rhetorical <hi>Numphs! Excluders with a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> what an Expreſſion is here? This <hi>Grubſtreet</hi> Vermin is a worthy Offe to write Compariſons of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> truly. But let us ſee what <hi>Excluders with a Witneſs</hi> were they? <hi>Oh,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſuch as were for Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> Mary <hi>Queen of</hi> Scots, <hi>not only from the Succeſſion, but out of the World.</hi> I'll warrant him he thinks he has nickt it here. What relation has that Queens Caſe to ours? She was under an Accuſation of a Conſpiracy againſt the Queen and the Government; nor was ever ſuch thing as a Bill of Excluſion againſt her thought of: But this Caſe of hers has been a ſtanding falſe Argument with all our Blockheadly Pamphletteers to this purpoſe theſe Three years: And our preſent Author who loves Common places ſo well as to make a whole Book of them, certainly could never miſs this, though I muſt beg leave to take notice to what purpoſe: Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from <hi>the Succeſſion,</hi> but <hi>out of the World!</hi> How villainouſly would he here inſinuate the Neceſſity of ſhedding more Royal Blood, when this miſerable Kingdom ſmells too rank of it already: And for the Caſe even of that unhappy Queen, It appeared to the eyes of all the World ſo horrid and prophane a Violation of the Rights of Majeſty, that the Memory öf it is an Odium upon us all over Chriſtendom to this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day.</p>
            <p>And for the muſty Piece of a <hi>Journal,</hi> which he is pleaſed to quote for the neceſſity of Cruelty and Bloodſhed, of a Writing as he ſtyles it, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Reaſons to prove the Queens Majesty bound in Conſcience to proceed with Severity in this Caſe of the late Queen of</hi> Scots. By his good leave, I think it no Argument at all to the preſent purpoſe, but the Writing it ſelf <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Sim. d'Ewes</hi> Journ.</note> in the quality of its matter Unchriſtian, and in its manner boyiſh and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous; fooliſhly Sophiſtical, without any foundneſs of Reaſoning, or ſtrength in Law: It ſayes in the firſt place, <hi>Every good Prince ought by God's Commandment to puniſh even with Death, all ſuch as ſeek to ſeduce the People of God, from his true Worſhip unto Superſtition and Idolatry; For that offence God hath always moſt grievouſly puniſhed, as committed againſt the firſt Table;</hi> and to prove this, they cite a Text of Scripture of <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. Now to make that Text of Scripture valid and of force to what we have in hand, we muſt Firſt have a Law of the Kingdom for the Puniſhment of Death in that Caſe. Secondly, That Law of the Kingdom muſt explain what this Idolatry is. Thirdly, After all, it muſt be ſuch an Idolatry as that Text of Scripture has expreſs'd, or elſe the Chapter is quoted to no purpoſe. As to the firſt, concerning a Law of the Kingdom for Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Death in that Caſe, I believe upon Examination we ſhall find none; for as our Author has juſtly obſerved in another place, that Law <hi>de Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico Comburendo</hi> is taken away: Beſides, granting there were a Capital Law againſt the Idolatry mentioned in that Chapter, I queſtion yet (to put the worſt of the Caſe) whether it would reach Popery or no: for if we examine Verſe the <hi>6th.</hi> of that Chapter, we ſhall find the Idolatry there mentioned to be explain'd, <hi>for the turning aſide to ſerve other Gods which we have not known, we nor our Fathers.</hi> Now I never heard but that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſerved and adored the very ſame God that we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93598:7"/>
do, in the Trinity of Perſons, and Unity of the Godhead: So that of this ſort of Idolatry, at leaſt ſhe does not appear to be guilty. What other Kind (for certainly there are different Kinds) may be lay'd to her Charge, I could wiſh ſome Ingenuous, Conſcientious, and Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Divine would for the true Information of all honeſt and truely Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Children of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> fairly, and candidly lay down and determine. I am ſure the canting, falſifying, and miſ-interpretation of Scripture, which ſuch Fellows as the Author of this Libel and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions uſe to ſerve their Malice or other Ends in Seducing and Impoſing upon the Ignorance of the Vulgar, tend rather to the bringing Popery in Credit again, than any thing elſe; and if the Author of <hi>The Growth of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery were alive,</hi> to add to that Treatiſe, I know not where he could raiſe a better Argument for his Theam, than from thoſe Scriblers, that are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to pretend the defence of the beſt and trueſt Religion in the World, by the falſeſt and worſt Arguments, that their Ignorance or Immorality can furniſh them withal.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, this Libel againſt the Chriſtian Religion; this <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, which has made ſo much noiſe in the World, I mean, amongſt the Ignorant ſince its Publication, is ſo far from being what it would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be, <hi>viz. An Argument againſt the D's Right of Succeſſion,</hi> that it is nothing but a downright Alarum to Rebellion; for as an Alarum in War is nothing but a confuſed Noiſe and Rattling upon a Drum without any meaſure, method, or diſtinction; ſo this Whole Book from one end to the other, is only an indiſtinguiſhable lump of Sedition, thrown out in a confuſed heap, to amuze and glut the Vulgar withal, without any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments raiſed from any principle, or tending to any end except that of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking our Swords into one anothers Bowels, drowning our Fields in blood, and overwhelming of our Peace for ever.</p>
            <p>How fooliſhly does he tugg and heave at an Argument which his Brains want ſtrength to ſet a going againſt that <hi>Popular one,</hi> as he calls it of our Allegiance ſworn to the King, and his Lawful Heirs and Succeſſors; by telling us what ſome Lawyers (that is to ſay of his own Set) think of the Matter, <hi>No Man can have an Heir while he himſelf is alive:</hi> Which though I think I have confuted in the following Anſwer to the <hi>Tory Plot,</hi> yet to come a little nearer him here, If no Man can have an Heir while he himſelf is alive, how came that diſtinction to be once urged in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, betwixt Heir Apparent, and Heir Preſumptive? The Noble Gentleman that made it underſtood Law, and I hope, good Mr. Author, you will not accuſe ſo great an Oracle as he has been to your Party of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; For, if the King can have no Heir while he himſelflives, that tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Duke how he was not Heir Apparent, but Heir Preſumptive, was a Nonſenſical Diſtinction to make the beſt of it, for he ought not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your Argumment to have allowed that the Duke was ſo much as Heir Preſumptive, but ought to have declared, That the King till he was dead could have no Heir at all; but I ſuppoſe he knew where he was, and was wiſer. What ſtuff too is this which follows againſt another Argument, which he ſays he has heard fetched from the Common Prayer, <hi>(viz.) That no Church of</hi> England <hi>Man can with a good Conſcience be for a Bill of Excluſion, which</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93598:7"/>
               <hi>they ſay is to the Prejudice of His Royal Highneſs,</hi> becauſe we there Pray, <hi>that God would proſper him with all Happineſs both here and hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To anſwer which, ſays he, <hi>it would be a Curſe either in the mouth or heart of any Proteſtant, under the name of Happineſs; to wiſh him the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, invincible Temptation, and a kind of Neceſſity to Extirpate the beſt Religion in the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now does not this Fellow deſerve to be pelted and hollow'd out of every Society that had but Common Senſe? <hi>Kind of Neceſſity!</hi> In the Devil's Name, what Conjuration's this! What does he mean by <hi>Kind of Neceſſity?</hi> Is not all Neceſſity the ſame? Are there any kinds of it? Thou Noddle full of unutterable Nonſenſe, there are ſeveral kinds of Conveniency indeed, but I never heard of kinds of Neceſſity before, as for Example, I could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſeveral kinds of Conveniencies for our Author, <hi>viz.</hi> It were convenient for him to learn Grammar; It were convenient for him to turn an Honeſt Man; It were convenient for him to get a good Parſonage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But for the Firſt, it may be he is too old or too dull; For the Second, I am afraid he has no Seeds of it in his Nature; For the Third, I am informed he has behaved himſelf ſo ſcandalouſly in one poſt already, that he will hardly be truſted in haſt with another (I know not what a new Patron may do for him) But it is abſolutely neceſſary for him to Eat in this World; Bread he muſt have, and he finding that playing the Knave and the Fool is the moſt agreeable way to his Nature of getting it, has very fairly ſet up his Trade with a <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate. This I take to be an illuſtrative deſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Neceſſity and Conveniency.</p>
            <p>But why, my dear Author (ſhould he ever ſucceed which may be, I hope, as much as you, that he will not, for I hope the King may out-live him.) But why will he have a Neceſſity upon him to Extirpate the beſt Religion in the World? I am afraid my little <hi>Mephiſtophilus</hi> may have a Quirk in this, for if by the beſt Religion in the World, thou meaneſt Presbytery, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, Anabaptiſm, Browniſm, Quakeriſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all blended together as they are already in a Faction, or either of them ſeparated from the reſt as it is probable thou mayeſt, my dear Author: verily, I am of thy Opinion. For I think it ſo abſolutely neceſſary for the too merciful Prince, who poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes the Throne already to do it, That I am afraid and perſwaded, They will never let him Rule in Peace ſo long as there is one of their Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> left to blow the Trumpets of Sedition, affront the Authority of the Government, and vex the Quiet, and the Peace of his Kingdoms. To Extirpate theſe falſe Religions, I think there is a kind of Neceſſity, as thou calleſt it; But how the D. ſhould he ſucceed will have by that a Neceſſity to Extirpate the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by the Law it is Eſtabliſhed, is a Riddle I would fain ſee interpreted; I believe he would find it abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary for him to do otherwiſe, I believe he may find it neceſſary for him to Preſerve, maintain, and Indulge that Religion, ſo eſſential to the Royal Authority it ſelf, that That, and the Beſt King fell together: and what ſort of Church ſucceeded, ask Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> The Church of <hi>England</hi> is a Religion whoſe intereſt is ſo mixed and interwoven, on one hand with the Prerogatives, Authority and Safety of the King; on the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93598:8"/>
other, with the Liberty, Property, Quiet and Eaſe of the Subject; in ſhort, ſo much the Golden Chain that tyes the Intereſt of Rule and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience together, that I dare pronounce no King can be Happy in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that does not in all its Intereſts and niceſt Points ſupport it. Nor will it for all the Preface to <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate be neceſſary for any Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to ſuffer its Diminution or its leaſt Impair, much leſs to extirpate and deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>All this Virulence and bitterneſs he has expreſſed in his Preface againſt the Duke of <hi>York.</hi> But when he comes to ſpeak of <hi>Julian,</hi> I deſire but the Reader to take notice how favourably he handles him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was,</hi> ſays he, <hi>a Law, and an Ancient Law of the Empire (and ſo great ſtreſs was laid upon it, that the breach of it was look't upon as an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the Government and the Empire) that every one ſhould Honour and Worſhip the Emperors Statues and Pictures which were ſet up for that end in Publick places. Now (</hi> ſays he) <hi>He</hi> (meaning his Friend <hi>Julian) took advantage of that Law to enſnare them unawares in Heatheniſh Worſhip, for he added the Figures of the Heathen Gods to his own Picture, and as</hi> Gregorie<hi>'s words are (this fellow has a great honour for</hi> Gregory, <hi>as we ſhall ſee hereafter) mingled Poiſon with their meat, abuſing their Loyalty to the purpoſes of Idolatry.</hi> Now let us Conſtrue this Gibberiſh, and ſee what it ſignifies.</p>
            <p>If there were a Law of the Empire for the worſhipping of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Statues and Pictures, then was Idolatry eſtabliſhed by Law, for worſhipping Statues is no better, and what a Libel has he made upon Chriſtianity; nay, and quoted <hi>Gregory</hi> for his Author, in telling us, <hi>That the Chriſtians thought themſelves bound in Loyalty to obey that Law:</hi> Or how (though the Pictures of the Heathen Gods were added to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours) was their Loyalty in Danger of being abuſed? for if thoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians could diſpence in Conſcience with adoring and worſhipping the Emperours Statues, they might eaſily have ſeparated their adoration from the Images of the Heathen Gods, and kept their Loyalty as found as ever it was; what ſtuff is this to be Publiſhed in Print! I am afraid the Preſs has got a Contagion of Nonſence, and will never vent wholſom Senſe and ſound Reaſoning agen; for I am fain to write almoſt as bad Nonſence as he to anſwer him: as ſome ſort of Poiſons are only to be expell'd by another.</p>
            <p>But to enquire a little farther, who were they that refuſed this? why he refers us to St. <hi>Gregory</hi> agen, who he ſays tells us, <hi>Some of the Wiſer and more Conſcientious found out the Fraud, but they paid for their Sagacity, the Pretence was, that they offended againſt the Honour of the Emperour; but the Truth was, they came into Danger for the ſake of the true King.</hi> Was there ever a Libel againſt Chriſtianity, and an Apology for an Apoſtate better couched? Here he accuſes thoſe Chriſtians of no leſs than Idolatry and Rebellion at once; of Idolatry, in that they made no ſcruple of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Statue of Emperour and of Rebellion in making a fooliſh evaſion to diſobey the Law in boggling at Images of the Heathen Gods being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93598:8"/>
preſent, which they need not have taken any notice of. But at the ſame time to Compliment <hi>Julian,</hi> ſays, <hi>They were puniſhed yet in no appearance, for not worſhipping the Heathen Images, but for offending the honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour;</hi> Nevertheleſs to gloſs and varniſh over the Bus'neſs, he calls it indeed a <hi>Pretence;</hi> and ſays the truth was, That <hi>they came in Danger for the ſake of the true King:</hi> And what does he mean by the true King now? I'le warrant you no leſs than <hi>King Jeſus.</hi> Were <hi>Venner</hi> alive at the Head of his Fifty Madmen once more, each Warrior whereof was to ſlay his Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; this Fellow, I fancy, would make a very good Chaplain to the Troop.</p>
            <p>But the end and ſcope of all this is, as I find a little after, to ſhoulder in a Parallel as he thinks of ſome body elſe; For, <hi>Now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>If a Prince puts a Border of Popery (which ſome ſay is ten times worſe than a Border of Paganiſm) about his Picture, which we fain would Honour and Reverence, and once did before we ſaw that unhappy Accident: What ſhall we ſay! or what can we do!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was there ever any thing ſo witty as this now? Does not this Fellow deſerve to be a Lord's Chaplain? a Character I hear he is lately prefer'd to for this very Piece. Was there ever any thing ſo newly Rhetorical! <hi>Border of Popery!</hi> Put prithee my Dear Deacon under the Roſe; why a Border of Popery after all? would it not have ſounded as well to have ſaid a Girdle of Popery, or a Shoulder Belt of Popery? beſides, it would have been a more lively Image of the thing, if the Shoulder Belt had been Embroidered into the Bargain, as it might have been with Triple Crowns, Beads, Crucifixes, Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfreye</hi>'s Murders, all the Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicks of the <hi>Raree Show,</hi> and at laſt Arbitrary Power in Capital Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, at the bottom of all upon the dreadful hangers; this upon reading might have darted dreadful Imaginat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons into our heads indeed, but <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Popery!</hi> Fye, fye, 'tis mean and little, a Taylor would have made as noble a Metaphor. Then too after all, to finiſh thy Period with <hi>what ſhall we ſay! what can we do!</hi> 's life, it puts me in mind of <hi>Shirley</hi>'s Part in the <hi>Rehearſal,</hi> viz. <hi>Heigho: Heigh day! I have no more to do, nor more to ſay!</hi> Though if the Laws ſhall once (as in due time my dear Friend 'tis poſſible) put a true Proteſtant <hi>Engliſh</hi> Halter, or a Border of a Pillory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy Neck: I know very well what the Executioner will do, and all Honeſt Men will be furniſhed with ſomething to ſay.</p>
            <p>I thought here to have done with his Preface, but upon farther Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, beg leave to remark upon one Paſſage more of it, and then go forward with the Bulk of his Libel.</p>
            <p>Speaking of the Diviſions of the Church at this time, ſays this worthy Reverend Author, <hi>Now what did the Chriſtians do? Did the Orthodox go and ſide with</hi> Julian <hi>to revenge the Injuries which they had received from the</hi> Arrians <hi>in</hi> Conſtantius's <hi>time! Or make uſe of</hi> Julian's <hi>favour which he ſhewed in reſtoring them to cruſh their Brethren, which differed from them!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us examine the Matter, and Judge what credit ought to be given to any thing this Fellow ſays hereafter: Firſt, he here declares <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93598:9"/>
a favourer of Arrianiſm, one that had Perſecuted and Baniſhed the Orthodox Chriſtians; yet afterwards makes him the Hero of his Romance, owns <hi>Julian</hi> the Favourer, Patron and Reſtorer of thoſe Orthodox Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from Baniſhment, yet would make us believe his Book intentionally Publiſhed to his Prejudice, when it will appear upon the whole Matter he hath done all that is poſſible to give <hi>Julian</hi> a Character of the moſt Moral and (ſetting aſide his Defection from the Faith) the more merciful Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror to the Chriſtians of the two; nay, and has the Impudence more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over to ſlur the Profeſſors in thoſe times of that moſt damnable Hereſie of Arrianiſm upon us for Primitive Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the Preface. Thus much for the Bulwark, now for the Gyant lodged within, and thus it begins: <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate, Chapter the Firſt. A ſhort Account of</hi> Julian<hi>'s Life;</hi> Let it come then in the Name of God, (as a great Man ſaid once of a Hare,) I fear it not.</p>
            <p>This Chapter being a ſhort Account of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Life, we may reaſonably ſuppoſe, ſince it is written by one that pretends not to praiſe him for his Vertues, we ſhall in it find Matters againſt him heinous enough to corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond with the odious Title it ſeems to bear. But if through this whole Chapter we find nothing (ſaving his Apoſtacy) laid to his Charge, but what the beſt and moſt merciful Prince in Moral Prudence might, nay, ought to have done; I hope the World will be of my Opinion in ſome meaſure at leaſt that our Author is not ſo much his Enemy as in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face he pretends to be.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing then that he ſays againſt him, (nay, and he quotes <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> for it too) Page the Fourth is, <hi>That having a Mind to the Scepter, and ſeeking, Fortune-tellers to know whether he ſhould obtain his deſire, he met with a Man that promiſed to foretel him theſe things, who led him into an Idol Temple, and there initiated him; ſo that the deſire of a Kingdom, ſtript this thrice wretched Perſon of his Piety;</hi> and yet the very next Line to prove his Friend <hi>Theodoret</hi> a Lyar, if poſſible, he calls <hi>Gregory</hi> to witneſs, <hi>That he had no Piety at that time to loſe.</hi> Is not this as Friendly an Office as poſſible to <hi>Julian</hi> to bring two ſuch Eminent Writers againſt him as <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> contradicting one another in Matter of Fact, and even in very Terms? <hi>And to proceed</hi> ſays he, (quoting <hi>Gregory</hi> ſtill) <hi>even before that he was a concealed Pagan, and Diſputed with his Brother in favour of the Heathens;</hi> when immediately to confound all truth that might hence be urged in this caſe againſt his Friend the Apoſtate, he tells us the very next Page, <hi>That nevertheleſs, the Fathers all agree, that the occaſion of</hi> Julian<hi>'s Revolt from Chriſtianity was from a thirſt of Empire, and from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting his heatheniſh</hi> Gadburies <hi>about it.</hi> So that in the firſt place, we have here <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaying, That by his following Soothſayers, his deſire of a Kingdom ſtript him of his Piety. Then <hi>Gregory</hi> telling us, He had at that time no Piety to loſe, being a concealed Pagan before; but to cloſe the Diſpute at laſt the conſent of the Fathers, that the Occaſion of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from Chriſtianity for all that, was from a thirſt of Empire, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting his Heathen <hi>Gadburies:</hi> Now if one ſhould object after all this, That the Fathers never knew or heard of ſuch a Name as <hi>Gadbury;</hi> why,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93598:9"/>
may be our Author will anſwer, It is a fine thing to be florid, with all my heart, but has not our Author to his Power afterwards juſtify'd <hi>Julian</hi>'s relyance on Aſtrology, by telling us how St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> has fully expreſt the Matter in few words, ſaying, <hi>That the ſame God who gave the Empire to a good Emperour, gave it likewiſe to</hi> Julian; ſo that for any thing I ſee, the <hi>Gadburies</hi> were very Honeſt <hi>Gadburies,</hi> and told him the truth at leaſt, how ill uſe ſoever he made of it. I am ſure he has proved <hi>Julian</hi> did not Uſurp it as is ſaid afterwards, but that God gave it him.</p>
            <p>Now to ſum up this which we have examined, all that I can find it vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly amount to, is, That our Author having a mind nothing ſhould be credited of what he ſays in his Book againſt <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, has taken the firſt opportunity to prove <hi>Gregory</hi> a Lyar, and overthrow his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that all the Quotations out of him, (which are almoſt the only, or at leaſt the moſt material ones he makes uſe of in the whole) might be eſteemed by the Reader of no force, as coming from a prejudiced hand, and one that in the very beginning had forfeited the Truth. I think no man under a kind of Neceſſity (as our Author has it) to write againſt <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in Publick, could have treated him underhand more like a Friend.</p>
            <p>Nay, He almoſt dares bare-faced undertake it; for after all this, as if he feared we might believe there was ſomething in the Matter: to confute the whole, he declares the very next Paragraph, <hi>That the World knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this, no, nor the Emperour himſelf:</hi> Juſt as if he would put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our mouths to ask then, how <hi>Theodoret, Gregory,</hi> and the Fathers came by the Story? or did <hi>Julian</hi> truſt them with it being Errant Chriſtians, and his particular Friends, and ſo they kept it as a ſecret from the World and the Emperour, leſt it might ſpoil his Succeſſion? This will not agree with the following Chapter, as we ſhall ſee by and by farther. In ſhort, Matters as to this Point are much in the dark, and I am almoſt at our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's own paſs, of <hi>what ſhall we do?</hi> or <hi>what can we ſay?</hi> All that I can think of it is, that Nonſence, Incoherency, and a mired underſtanding are a juſt Judgment upon a Scribling Varlet, that has no more Grace than to write againſt his Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The next Account we have of <hi>Julian</hi> is, <hi>That being made</hi> Caeſar <hi>by the Emperour, and ſent with an Army againſt ſome Northern</hi> Barbarians <hi>who had invaded</hi> France, <hi>he proved very ſucceſsful and routed the Enemy; upon which, having got the hearts of the Common Souldiers by giving them Money, they declared hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Emperour:</hi> Now in all reaſonable Conjecture, thoſe Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers might make him Emperour even againſt his Will, or at leaſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his ſeeking. For <hi>Conſtantius</hi> being a favourer of Arrianiſm, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Baniſhed the Orthodox, theſe Souldiers being (as our Author plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledges, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>8th.) Men Principled in the true Religion might do it for the Intereſt of that Truth, in hopes he might recall the Orthodox, as he afterwards did.</hi> Nevertheleſs, do but obſerve how he uſes <hi>Gregory</hi> again upon this occaſion, for, having done his beſt to prove him a Lyar before, here he's reſolved to make him little better than a Fool too: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Julian Marching with his Army towards</hi> Conſtantinople. <hi>Gregory</hi> tells us, (Alas poor <hi>Gregory!) That his pretence was, he came to excuſe his</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93598:10"/>
               <hi>being made Emperour; but the truth was, to wreſt the Empire out of</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius<hi>'s hands, who thereupon waved his</hi> Perſian <hi>Expedition, and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with his Army to meet him, but died by the way: elſe</hi> Julian <hi>had paid for his Folly.</hi> Now what is this, but Covertly to inſinuate to us how far <hi>Gregory</hi> was behind hand in the account of Common ſenſe, to think that ſo great a Captain as <hi>Julian</hi> was, would venture to March with a new uſurped Authority, uncertain of the hearts of his Army (which he ſays af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he found much difficulty to gain) againſt a Potent Emperour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in his Authority, beloved by his People, and ſecure in the midſt of the ſtrength of his Empire. What is this, but ſecretly to call <hi>Gregory</hi> an Aſs to think ſo, and confirm the Sincerity of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Obedience, in that he came purpoſely, as he indeed pretended, to deliver up the Authority which he thought he could not hold without Diſhonour; what greater Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrick can a Parſon make upon an Apoſtate?</p>
            <p>Next, ſays our Author, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> Julian <hi>having called home the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Biſhops whom</hi> Conſtantius <hi>Baniſh'd, and thus ſettled himſelf in his Throne, and made the Army ſure to him, he began to diſcover his Malice againſt the Chriſtians:</hi> Well, but how? (I dare venture to looſe odds, if this double-dealing Deacon does not bring his Friend the Apoſtate off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain preſently:) <hi>Vous avez,</hi> Page the <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
               </hi> He charged the People, <hi>That they ſhould Injure none of the Chriſtians, nor reproach them, nor draw them to Sacrifice againſt their wills.</hi> Was there ever ſo impudent a Fellow as this Chaplain of my Lord's!</p>
            <p>Nay, ſo very tender is he of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Reputation in this Point, that when he comes to ſpeak of any ill uſage which the Chriſtians received, He does all that poſſibly can be done to let us underſtand <hi>Julian</hi> had not any hand in the Bus'neſs: As for inſtances, <hi>The Heathens,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ran about the ſtreets, and abuſed the Saints with Scurrility and Mockery, and omitted no ſort of reproachful and abuſive Language.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this, as our Author has ordered the matter, is ſo far from refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting upon <hi>Julian,</hi> that it utterly clears him of the thing: For he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore charged his People not <hi>to reproach them,</hi> &amp;c. Nor will his pretence of telling us <hi>Julian</hi> connived at it ſerve his turn; for it is well known Kings, and Emperours in thoſe times did not uſe ſo to trifle with their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to Command their People one thing, and then ſuffer their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to fly in the face of their Authority, and commit Riots in ſpight of them.</p>
            <p>But upon enquiry, we ſhall find this worthy Author had a farther drift, which was to expoſe <hi>Gregory</hi> for a Mad man, as he had done before for a Fool and a Lyar. And he goes about it thus:</p>
            <p>After having told us a Story, <hi>how the Heathens and Chriſtians uſed to rail at one another in Streets, much like the Scolding of our Watermen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the</hi> Thames, <hi>till at laſt they came to blows, in which the Chriſtians came by the worſt of it,</hi> he proceeds to tell us a Story of one <hi>Cyril,</hi> a <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con that was killed for being a hot-headed over Zealous Fool at</hi> Heliopolis,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93598:10"/>
               <hi>and breaking down many of the Images which were there worſhipped:</hi> Now I think the <hi>Deacon</hi> deſerved to have his addled Brains beat out as they were for letting his Zeal tranſport him to the breach of the publick Peace and the Laws, I am at this high noon of Chriſtianity for hanging up all zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diſturbers of the publick, I am for hanging up thoſe zealous true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of an adjacent County, that lately broke open a Church, threw down the Communion-Table, &amp; defaced the Altar becauſe they thought it an abomination, nay afterwards defiled the publick Veſſel of Baptiſm, &amp; tore the Bible the bleſſed word of God, for the ſhameful uſe that followed.</p>
            <p>But to what we propoſed, this ſtory of <hi>Cynril</hi> is followed by another <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Marcus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arethuſa,</hi> who had thrown down a Temple that belonged to the <hi>Heathens</hi> and built a Chriſtian Church in the ſtead of it, upon which the people of <hi>Arethuſa</hi> demanding of him to rebuild their Temple, or pay a certain Summ of Money equivalent, he refuſed and was killed for his pains; nay our Author tells us, they would have compounded with him for one piece of Gold, but he ſaid no.</p>
            <p>Now if this be true, I do not think that this Biſhop of <hi>Arethuſa</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf like a conſcientious or a wiſe Biſhop. For in the firſt place he had no right that impowered him to throw down the Temple at all, and might Twenty to one have found many as convenient places to have built his Chriſtian Church in as that was, and have done the publick property no Injury neither<hi>:</hi> Now it may be 'twill be objected, that it was the impulſe of his Zeal; to which I anſwer, I am not for that Zeal that blows up Houſes and demoliſhes Temples, let the pretence be as plauſible as it will, we have had enough of ſuch Zeal in <hi>England</hi> already to our ſorrow and our ſhame<hi>:</hi> This ſtory our Author urges as inſtance of the perſecution Chriſtianity lay under at that time, where I deſire only the Reader to obſerve he has taken care not to make <hi>Julian</hi> appear in it at all, he is all along very tenderly careful of <hi>Julians</hi> reputation and will rather make one of his Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Biſhops (as he calls 'em) appear a Fool or a Mad-man then urge any thing that may reflect too cloſely upon his favourite Apoſtate; But for his old acquaintance, <hi>Gregory</hi> to make him as I ſaid before as much a Mad-man as is poſſible: though he cites this inſtance of <hi>Marcus</hi> for an example of cruelty and injuſtice, he tells us Page the <hi>12th.</hi> Gregory <hi>was of opinion (and he calls it a ſharp ſaying of him) that</hi> Marcus <hi>juſtly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all this, and deſerved to have ſuffered a great deal more for that he once ſaved</hi> Julian: Methinks now <hi>Gregory</hi> had a very odd Notion of Juſtice according to this Argument<hi>:</hi> but the truth of the matter is, that he is mightily beholding to our Author through his whole book upon all occaſions. But now to cloſe this ſhort account which he gives us of the Life of <hi>Julian,</hi> I deſire the Reader to obſerve if any thing could be more elaborate to raiſe an Argument in his praiſe then our Author has been. For whereas he urges (and Quotes one <hi>Socrates</hi> for it too) how <hi>Julian</hi> by a Law commanded that the Children of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhould have no Schooling or Education, leſt by this advantage they might be better able to oppoſe the diſputants of the Gentiles, Page the 14th. <hi>To oppoſe and utterly refute this Charge againſt him he cites</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93598:11"/>
               <hi>himſelf declaring (Juliani Ep.</hi> 42.) It would be an unjuſt thing to barr Children which knew not which way to turn themſelves, from the right way, and ſaying expreſly, that their Children were not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited: But mark the ſubtilty of the Man how craftily he couches this Apology for <hi>Julian,</hi> by ſaying, who would ſend their Children to <hi>Heathen</hi> Maſters, where they ſhould be principled in Heatheniſm? And that this Liberty forſooth was one of <hi>Julians</hi> Traps wherein conſiſted the true ſpirit of his perſecution. Now durſt our Author have ſpoken out I fancy he would have told us—Ah, Beloved <hi>Julian</hi> 'tis true was an Apoſtate, but indeed a moral man, and a very merciful Prince, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Chriſtians tis true; but how! Ah Beloved, not with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables and Militia-men diſturbing their Conventicles, not by a Statute of the <hi>35th</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> he perſecuted them by Indulgency, by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience; My Beloved, 'twas in that conſiſted the true ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Julians</hi> perſecution, <hi>Julian</hi> was a merciful Perſecutor but <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is plainer if meaning be to be gathered out of words then that this was our Authors drift in what he delivers us concerning the Apoſtate, how wide ſoever he pretends to fly and ſqueek from the matter, the <hi>Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wings</hi> Neſt is not where the noiſe is made; yet he has not ſo cloſely cover'd his cheat neither but that a diſcerning eye may eaſily diſcover what I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved before in the beginning of theſe remarkes, that his whole book from one end to the other, is but a defence of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for Apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>Thus I have done with this ſhort account of <hi>Julians</hi> life, wherein I think I have ſufficiently diſcovered and made appear that our Author has been much his friend, and recoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d nothing that <hi>Julian</hi> has done (ſetting aſide his Apoſtacy) to render his Character odious to any cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Reader, or to charge him with the leaſt perſecution of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity through his whole Government, though I ſhould not have taken this way of anſwering ſuch a Book, or perhaps not medled with it at all, But that the vile, ſeditious deſign and villanous of it provoked me to expoſe the Ignorance, and Folly of an Arrogant Dunce that would needs be waſting Ink and Paper, without a common portion of Logick to argue from any principle, or raiſe (though we ſhould be ſo civil to grant what he knows not how to propoſe) the leaſt reaſonable conſequence. The whole Book being but a few chew'd ſcraps, and mammocks of <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> cholerick invectives, which perhaps he had better have ſet alone then ever publiſhed, and certainly would have done ſo had he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, what a ridiculous uſe ſuch a little greecling as this Scribler would have made of them.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the little peeviſh inſect would fain by its buzz, inſinuate into the world that this Impertinent Collection may in ſome meaſure bear a Parallel with the preſent caſe of a Prince, whom I will not diſhonour ſo much as to name, upon an occaſion ſo unworthy his meaneſt conſideration, I have taken upon me for the rectifying and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſing of the underſtandings of a great many poor deluded people, that I am informed have been led away by the ſpeciouſneſs of the pretence, without conſidering the weight of the argument, to waſh off the Guelt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93598:11"/>
from this ſhining piece of Nonſence ſhew the vile unvaluable droſs it is compoſed of, and let them ſee what a Knave they have to deal with, for putting ſuch falſe Metal upon them, and what a Fool he was too, that could counterfeit the Stamp and Coyn of ſence and honeſty no better.</p>
            <p>And to this end, I ſhall proceed in the Examination of his Second Chapter, which he calls the ſence of the Primitive Chriſtians about <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>18th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Julians</hi> Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>Now in a diſcourſe under theſe contents, A Man would reaſonably imagine we were to be treated (conſidering the end our Author drives at) with an account of ſome publick Acts and Endeavours of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to obſtruct and cut off the Succeſſion of this <hi>Julian,</hi> we might expect here ſome preſident for an Act of Excluſion, warranted from a practice of ſo ancient a ſtanding as that of the Primitive Chriſtians, as our Author calls them, in <hi>Conſtantius</hi>'s time, tho they were indeed <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> but inſtead of that in the very beginning of this Chapter we are told we cannot expect, to read of any endeavours uſed to prevent this Succeſſion, and to fore-cloſe him upon the ſcore of his Religion. And why? Becauſe ſayes our Author, <hi>Julians coming to the Crown a Pagan was a perfect ſurprize to the World:</hi> ſo that inſtead of giving us here a Preſident for an Act of Excluſion even in the like caſe, all he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us of is, That it was the ſence of the Primitive Chriſtians not to fore cloſe, as he calls it, any one upon the ſcore of his Religion, at leaſt before they knew of his defection. Now here is a neat way of arguing this Fellow has, when he would compare and make Parallels, is it not? All I ſay from hence is, if it were the opinion of the Primitives, I think it ought to be the ſence of us that are Chriſtians too, if Religion and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice be not growing into contempt among us, not to fore-cloſe any man upon the ſcore of his Religion, till we are ſure at leaſt (from better Arguments then the malitious inſinuations of his Enemies, <hi>(whom he has a ſpirit too Royal and too great to bow to) and the Oaths of perjur'd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate Villains) that he has left it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come as near to the buſineſs he would foiſt upon us as is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which is to tell us the ſence of the Chriſtians at that time (I'l put the caſe modeſtly for him) concerning <hi>Julians</hi> Succeſſion, The firſt thing he does in this Chapter, (after a merry frisk or two by way of bob to Addreſſers in the beginning meerly to ſhew the nimble diſpoſition of his parts) is, to give us the moſt accurate account he can of <hi>Julians</hi> undoubted and indiſputable right to the Empire; and truly to do him Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice it is the only methodical, reaſonable &amp; well joyned ſtory or diſcourſe in his whole Book. After he has ſhown us this, bleſs us<hi>!</hi> how he ſeems to extend and raiſe himſelf for the force of the blow that is to follow; but let us ſee how we can bear it.</p>
            <p>After he had ſummed up the ſhort Hiſtory of <hi>Julians</hi> right to the Empire, he has pleaſed to expreſs himſelf thus. <hi>If this will not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>do, I know not what meaſures of divine right</hi> (ſpeaking you muſt know very deſpicably of the Aſſertors of any ſuch right) <hi>will ſerve their turn, unleſs</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93598:12"/>
               <hi>they would have a Crown drop from the Clouds.</hi> And yet ſayes he, <hi>The Fathers had the conſcience to ſet aſide ſuch a Title as this:</hi> Well, we deſire to ſee how, and that's but reaſonable. Why ſayes he, <hi>Gregory</hi> after <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> was dead, (he very much given to <hi>Gregory,)</hi> in the very beginning of an Invective calls after <hi>Conſtantius</hi> in Heaven, and expoſtulates the matter with him there. That is to ſay, after <hi>Julian</hi> was dead, <hi>Gregory</hi> calls <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2d.</hi>
               </note> after <hi>Conſtantius</hi> who dyed before him, to paſs a Bill of Excluſion and ſet aſide the Apoſtates Title to the Throne; is it not ſo? <hi>Riſum tenea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis amici!</hi> Now ſayes our worſhipful Author at the end of this Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Page the 24th, <hi>here is enough to ſhew that</hi> Conſtantius <hi>would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have made</hi> Julian Caeſar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now I think this as neat a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as the Argument will bear, I think the point of Succeſſion as handſomely ſettled, as any ſerupulous man could in conſcience deſire: I think our Author has ſatisfied us, That the Fathers would have ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide <hi>Julians</hi> Title to ſecure their Religion, for <hi>Gregory</hi> ſayes he, called after <hi>Conſtantius</hi> about it, when they were both dead and told him, the Apoſtate ought not to ſucceed: and that was as well as if all the Fathers had remonſtrated to him in his life time. <hi>Gregory</hi> good man, honeſt <hi>Gregory</hi> did all he could in the buſineſs he was for ſhutting the Stable Door according to the Proverb: <hi>his wiſdom truly was great, but it was ſomething Phrygian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now either the Fathers would have remonſtrated to <hi>Conſtantius</hi> in his life time againſt <hi>Julians</hi> Succeſſion, and forgot to tell us ſo, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Roſe</hi> our Author doth prevaricate, which in plain Engliſh is little better then Lying, or elſe they deputed <hi>Gregory</hi> to do it for them, and he like a falſe Brother, Father, writ invectives in his own name, and got all the honour of Expoſtulating againſt <hi>Julians</hi> Succeſſion, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was dead to himſelf. But to be ſerious a little, if upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion it be poſſible.</p>
            <p>And under a great tryal of my patience I ſpeak it, This Monſter of an Author is ſo unconſcionably dull, and has ſo little mercy on thoſe that fall under the Condemnation of reading him, that after having thus Quoted <hi>Gregory</hi> like a Coxcomb to a purpoſe for which every body that peruſes it with the leaſt attention muſt laugh at and deſpiſe him, he cannot forbear glutting us with more Impertinency ſtill, and telling us that the ſame Father will give us better meaſure in another place, now this other place is, but another piece of the old <hi>Gregorian</hi> Invective, As our Author hath tranſlated him; yet I will take pains to tranſcribe a little of it. I would give our Author, and his friend <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> as fair play as I can, and thus it runs.</p>
            <p>What have you done, O Divineſt Emperor and greateſt love of Chriſt, (for I am fallen to reprehending you, as if you were preſent <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ark it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ech ye.</note> and in hearing, although I know you to be much above my reproof, being placed with God, and inheriting the glory which is there, and are only gone from hence to Exchange your Kingdom) what ſtrange kind of Council is this which you have taken, who did far excel all other Kings in wiſdom and underſtanding<hi>!</hi> Thus has our Author
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93598:12"/>
Tranſlated it; now I deſire the Reader to accept of my Tranſlation upon this Tranſlation, and ſee if it ſerve not as well to the purpoſe. As thus then:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hubbubbeo!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vat aſt dou don noow dou diveeneſt Imperour and in Creat favourſhip vid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Iriſh</hi> houl in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner over their dead friends Graves and much to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> 
               <hi>Creeſt gra. for I muſt make expoſtulation upon dee as if dou didſt hear me doe dou doſt not hear me indeed neider vy voudſt dou dy I pridee now and leave dy Couſin</hi> Julian <hi>all dy Land and Poſſeſſions dou voo hadst ſo much Viſdom and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity St.</hi> Patrick <hi>be vid dy ſhweet ſhoule vy didst dou make dye amongst us!</hi> This really to me ſounds as reaſonably and as much to the purpoſe as the very other; yet ſuch ſtuff as this dares this dull Miſcreant quote for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that the Fathers would in Conſcience have ſet aſide <hi>Julian</hi>'s Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for the ſake of Religion, when he cites nothing to prove his Aſſertion but two or three ſcraps of a railing Invective; Publiſhed perhaps not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably after <hi>Julian</hi>'s Death as a piece of Eccleſiaſtical Policy, but ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies nothing to the preſent uſe he would make of it: Nor can there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be given to the very Tenure of it in general any credit at all: For whereas he ſays before, <hi>That</hi> Conſtantius <hi>would not have made</hi> Julian Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, <hi>nor have ſet up an Enemy of Chriſt over the Chriſtians, if he had known him to have been ſuch;</hi> yet he tells us not three leaves afterwards, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> (nay, and he quotes <hi>Grogory</hi> again for that too) <hi>That</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius <hi>made his Excuſe both to God and Man for his kindneſs to</hi> Julian, <hi>and repented him of it at his laſt breath:</hi> Now if <hi>Conſtantius</hi> knew not <hi>Julian</hi> to be an Apoſtate, he had no reaſon for this Repentance; if he did know him to be ſuch, he might perhaps have hindered his Succeſſion, but he did not; which plainly overthrows the uſe our Author makes of his Friend <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s Invective, which he ſays <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>24th, was enough to ſhew that</hi> Conſtantius <hi>never would have made</hi> Julian Caeſar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as I recited before. In ſhort, this Fellow had got a few Notions in his Head which his watry Brains were too cold to digeſt, ſo there they lay heavy till they infected him with that Epidemical Diſeaſe which rages of late ſo fatally amongſt us called <hi>Pruritus ſcribendi</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Scabies ſoeculi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what Apology can there poſſibly be made for a Fellow that talks at the rate he does in another place, <hi>viz.</hi> Page the <hi>27th.</hi> where he ſays (and calls it a Remarque of his own wiſe Noddle too) <hi>that the making of</hi> Julian <hi>a</hi> Caeſar, <hi>was a raſh, fooliſh, inconſiderate, cruel, inhumane action, and fit only for ſome Devil to adviſe;</hi> when but a little before, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>24th.</hi> he brings in <hi>Gregory</hi> Complimenting <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who did that Action, by the glorious Appellations of <hi>Divineſt Emperour,</hi> and <hi>greateſt Love of Chriſt.</hi> But as I have obſerved before, he never deſigned <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s advantage as to this bus'neſs in the leaſt; if he did, I am ſure he has ſpoil'd it, as bad as the Patron did him, who remov'd him from his Reader-ſhip in <hi>Covent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garden,</hi> to a Rector-ſhip in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or any where elſe.</p>
            <p>Now to what purpoſe our Author has written this Chapter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſenſe of the Primitive Chriſtian's about <hi>Julian</hi>'s Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and how far he has proved the Fathers in Conſcience would have ſet aſide his Title, I leave to the Judgment of any unbyaſſed and reaſonable underſtanding, and ſo beg leave to proceed to his Third
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93598:13"/>
Chapter, being an Account of the Chriſtian's behaviour towards <hi>Julian</hi> in words.</p>
            <p>Well, Now let us ſee then how they really did uſe him in their words, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>33d.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Why</hi> ſays our Author, <hi>inſtead of</hi> Julianus, <hi>they called him</hi> Idolianus, that is to ſay, they Quibbled upon him; was there ever ſuch ſtuff as this publiſhed before! Nay, ſays he farther, <hi>They called him</hi> Piſaeus, <hi>and</hi> Adonaeus <hi>from his worſhipping of</hi> Jupiter <hi>and</hi> Adonis: yet this Boyiſh ſtuff the fooliſh Fellow that writes it in the next Page, calls being <hi>ſmart</hi> upon <hi>Julian,</hi> I have an honour for a Jolt headed Deacon that's good at a Jeſt with all my heart.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew us more and more how he bears a Brain (as ſome old <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>35th.</hi>
               </note> Women call it) to convince us throughly how bitter the Chriſtians were upon all occaſions againſt this Emperour in their words and ſpeeches, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he quotes us out of <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> how that when he went to the <hi>Campaign, ſome of them wiſhed him a happy Expedition, and a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Return</hi> (bitter railing, this is very bitter railing!) Now has not this Scribler ordered this Chapter to as good purpoſe as he did the laſt! This is being very ſevere in their words and ſpeeches. This is being very ſmart upon him truly.</p>
            <p>Well, but now let us ſee how <hi>Julian</hi> revenged himſelf, and perſecuted them for this Treatment, and for it take this Story, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>36th.</hi> of a Nobleman of <hi>Berea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Nobleman,</hi> ſays our Author, <hi>having diſinherited his Son for Warp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>36th</hi> and <hi>37th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>towards the falſe Religion. This perſecuting</hi> Julian <hi>promiſing the Youth to reconcile his Father to him, invited the Magiſtrates and Chief men of</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea <hi>to a Feaſt, among the reſt this young Man and his Father, whom he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to ſit next himſelf</hi> (very horrid Perſecution indeed!) well but what followed: <hi>Why about middle of Dinner</hi> Julian <hi>ſays to the Father, In my mind it is not Juſt to force a Man's Judgment againſt his will: Therefore do not you force your Son againſt his mind to follow your Opinion; for neither do I force you to follow mine;</hi> ſo that here is Liberty of Conſcience ſtill, the true ſpirit of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Perſecution, as our Author obſerved before. Well, but what ſaid the old Gentleman to all this? why, the Father ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening his diſcourſe anſwered, <hi>O King, do you ſpeak of this Villain who is hated of God, and has preferr'd a Lye before the true Religion?</hi> Now cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a Tyrant, and Perſecutor, could do no otherwiſe than command him to be Hanged, Burned or Rack't for this at leaſt. Well, what did he do? why ſays our Author, <hi>he put on a Vizard of Meekneſs, and only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, Friend leave Railing.</hi> Now would not any one that reads this, fairly conclude that the reciter of it was more <hi>Julian</hi>'s Friend than the Nobleman's, and has given a better Character of the Apoſtate, than the Chriſtian?</p>
            <p>He tells us indeed another blind Story of a Blind Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>38th.</hi>
               </note> who was very foul mouthed towards <hi>Julian,</hi> for which he ſays, <hi>he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted him grievouſly afterwards;</hi> but the manner he leaves us to find out as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93598:13"/>
well as we can, he being as I think I have juſtly obſerved all along, too much a will-wiſher to <hi>Julian,</hi> to deliver any thing that ſhall not make rather for his Praiſe, than his Diſhonour: And this is really what his Third Chapter amounts to, in an account of what the Chriſtians behaviour was towards <hi>Julian</hi> in Words; we now come to conſider the next, namely the Fourth Chapter, and in that their Actions.</p>
            <p>The firſt Story whereof is that of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> which if it redound not as much to <hi>Julian</hi>'s honour, both for his Prudence, Temperance, Juſtice, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>39th.</hi>
               </note> and yet Mercy too, there is no credit to be given to <hi>Theodoret,</hi> or our Author's quotation of him: But the Reader may pleaſe to obſerve, That <hi>Theodoret</hi>'s Reputation was cleared at the beginning of theſe Remarks by the conſent of the Fathers; though honeſt <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s evidence to ſpeak modeſtly, was not altogether ſo clear as the Sun.</p>
            <p>And if this Story do prove ſo much to <hi>Julian</hi>'s advantage, according as it is delivered by our Author, I hope our Author will be ſo ingenuous the next time he has occaſion to appear in Print upon the behalf of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, as fairly to throw off the Hypocrites Cloak, declare to us freely how much he is an Apoſtates humble Servant, and tell us whoſe Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain he is<hi>:</hi> And thus it begins.</p>
            <p>Valentinian, <hi>being a concealed Chriſtian Collonel of Horſe under the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate</hi> Julian, <hi>and waiting upon his Maſter once in a Proceſſion to the Temple of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>39th.</hi>
               </note> Fortune: <hi>The Chaplains ſtood on both ſides of the Doors, cleanſing with ſprinklings thoſe that entered in. But when Collonel</hi> Valentinian <hi>ſaw this Holy Water coming near his Cloaths, he ſtruck the Chaplain with his Fiſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>40th.</hi>
               </note> ſaying, <hi>It would not cleanſe, but defile him:</hi> Now all I can diſcover out of this firſt part of the Story is, that <hi>Valentinian</hi> may be was a very ſpruce Collonel, and did not love to have his Embroider'd Coat uſed too fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly: For example, ſuppoſe even at home here in our little <hi>England,</hi> nay, at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> an Officer newly having bought his Place, going up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Duty, with a fine Beaver Hat, and a dainty unfully'd white Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in it, this Hat cockt too <hi>à la Francois,</hi> and under it a Perruque eſſenced and Curled in defiance to the ſmell of Match behind him, under his Chin an exquiſite Crevat, made up as dext'rouſly, as if he had done it himſelf by his own great Rules of Fortification, adorned moreover with a ſtrut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting String, that ſhews the exact Diameter of the <hi>Hero</hi>'s Phyſiognomy. Upon his Martial Body, a more Martial Coat: Round his fine Waſt a heavy Scarff, that loads his feeble bending Loins, and by his doughty, jetting, ſtrutting Side, a little pretty ſhort Sword, that would not hurt a Worm. Suppoſe him thus with all his <hi>fierte</hi> about him, Marching in Querpo for the defence of the Court, and the terrour of its ſlovenly Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and grant ſome Brewer's Dray juſt rumbling by; the frothy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter working from the Bungholes of the Barrels, and at every jolt, ſquirting as wonderfully as Sir <hi>S</hi>'s Engine; grant too, that ſome of it by accident might Contaminate the outſide, and better part of this Noble Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: ought not a well-dreſt Centurion upon this occaſion to exert himſelf, ſhew his Indignation of new Ale, and Value for new Clothes? Oh, but our Author will tell me there is difference between the ſprinklings of holy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93598:14"/>
Water, and ſpoutings of Yeaſt: If he does, I confeſs he will be in the right, and <hi>Valentinian</hi> was but an impudent unmannerly fellow to offer ſuch an act of Violence in the preſence of his Emperour, and againſt the Sacred Perſon (for ſo the Government then eſteemed them) of a Prieſt in the Performance of his Office: But to proceed, what ſaid <hi>Julian</hi> to all this? <hi>Why,</hi> Julian <hi>ſeeing what paſſed, ſent him away to a Garriſon lying by a Deſart,</hi> or as our Author quotes St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> for <hi>the purpoſe, turn'd him out of the Guards.</hi> Now all I can diſcover out of this ſecond Part of the Story is, that when this ſawcy Companion had flown in his Maſter's face, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>41ſt.</hi>
               </note> he turn'd him fairly out of his place; but gave him no leave to ſell: So that making Money of ill Manners was not in faſhion at <hi>Julian</hi>'s Court.</p>
            <p>Nor can <hi>Valentinian</hi>'s being a Chriſtian, and Zealous againſt the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry of the Pagans in any manner excuſe him, for if his Conſcience was too ſqueamiſh for his Employment, he ought honeſtly to have quitted his Command, and ſo have avoided the occaſion of either conſenting to thoſe Superſtitious Idolatrous Ceremonies, or committing a rude Irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent act in the Preſence, and againſt the Dignity of his Prince, his known Pleaſure, and his Lawes. For it is falſe which our Author in ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Book endeavours to inſinuate, <hi>That Christianity at that time was the Eſtabliſhed Religion of the Empire:</hi> For the Empire at that time being Univerſal, and of all the World, it cannot be imagined that Chriſtianity then but in it's Infancy, could already have prevailed ſo far as to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the general Law of the World, when even in theſe our times ſo many Ages ſince, it has much ado to keep the little ground it has got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten within the narrow bounds of <hi>Europe,</hi> the leaſt fourth Part of that Empire which he ſayes it was Eſtabliſhed in. Nay if we look but back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the <hi>8th</hi> page in the firſt Chapter, we ſhall find our Author him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Acknowledging, (and ſtill Quoting <hi>Gregory</hi> for it too) that of all this Eſtabliſhed Religion, there was indeed above 7000 left that did not bow the Knee to <hi>Baal.</hi> A Mighty Number to Eſtabliſh the Religion of the World withal! No, I am afraid the Religion according to Law at that time, was the Religion of the Emperour; and when <hi>Valentinian</hi> Broke the Laws by affronting of it, <hi>Julian</hi> (according to our obſervation in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Chapter) did like a Juſt Prince to puniſh him, Yet like a Merciful Prince to puniſh him ſo mildly. Like a Prudent Prince never farther to Employ or Truſt him, Yet like a Temperate Ruler too to Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify the Paſſions that probably ſo great a provocation might raiſe in him, with knowing well how to apply the Vertue, and Authority of his Laws. And this Praiſe I think our Author has taken a great deal of pains to give him, by telling the World the Story of <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Inſtance is, how old <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazianzum,</hi> our Author's Friend, <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Father, deny'd Entrance to a Captain of Archers, ſent by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>41ſt.</hi>
               </note> the Emperour to take poſſeſſion of a Church: upon which the Officer withdrew, I ſuppoſe according to his Orders too. Now all I can gather from hence is; The old Biſhop being refractory, the Emperour in pity proceeded with no farther Violence againſt him; for it cannot be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that <hi>Julian</hi> could want force (had he pleaſed) to have taken the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs. <hi>Oh but,</hi> ſayes our Author) <hi>Examine</hi> Gregory<hi>'s Funeral Speech upon</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93598:14"/>
               <hi>his Father's Death, and you ſhall find, that had not</hi> Julian <hi>got out of the Old Gentleman's way, he might have gone away Kickt;</hi> Tho this, if truly Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſounds to me rather like a Braggadochio of <hi>Gregory</hi> for the honour of his Father, then any thing elſe. (For I cannot believe that an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour would go himſelf in perſon to ſtorm a poor old doating decrepit Biſhop out of a little Pariſh Church;) yet our Author is very poſitive in the point, and ſayes, <hi>He had much a do to refrain making Soloeciſms in the Greek, to avoid the greater Soloeciſm of An Emperour of the World awed and terrify'd with the fear of a Kicking.</hi> This we are to underſtand is a merry <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>43d.</hi>
               </note> Conceit; But our Author, who loves to be ſure, gives us a Comment of a certain Metropolitan of <hi>Crete</hi> upon the place, which being too long to recite here, the Reader at his leiſure may peruſe, where he will find men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Captain of thoſe Archers indeed; but if <hi>Julian</hi> be named in it, I deſire to forfeit my Credit with him for ever. <hi>Well but</hi> (ſayes our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) <hi>this Metropolitan was a better Graecian than ever I expect to be;</hi> But by this he gives us room to obſerve that he expects to be a Metropolitan, though at leaſt, and ſurely he deſerves it, for writing ſo noble a Hiſtory of Primitive Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>And now ſayes our Author, page the <hi>44th, I know no more then the Pope of</hi> Rome <hi>what to make of all this, what they meant by it, or upon what Principles theſe men proceeded,</hi> (this is a familiar way of expreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but ô my Conſcience the man ſpeaks truth.) <hi>whether,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>Old</hi> Gregory <hi>diſtinguiſhed, and did not reſiſt</hi> Julian, <hi>but only the Devil which his Son ſo often tells us was in him.</hi> Ah Friend of mine have a care there; Theſe ſorts of diſtinctions may ſtand You in ill ſtead one day: for ſhould you by theſe diſtinctions cheat your ſelf into a ſhare in ſuch a Rebellion, as theirs was who ſaid <hi>they fought not againſt the King but his ill Miniſters about him,</hi> and then ſhould be hanged for your Logick, what an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate would Paganiſm loſe, and what a Chaplain his Lordſhip!</p>
            <p>But if ever the Deacon our Author were drunk in his life, (which is not a thing impoſſible, For there is very good Ale in <hi>Eſſex)</hi> certainly he had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>45th.</hi>
               </note> taken a Cup, when he wrote the ſucceeding Chapter concerning the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions of his Primitive Arrian Chriſtians about this buſineſs. <hi>For</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>when they go to Church and enter upon holy ground, there one may expect to ſee the flights of their ſelf-denying and ſuffering Religion; There one may expect they ſhould lay aſide all their animoſities, and pray for</hi> Julian <hi>though he were their enemy. Yes</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>and ſo they do the wrong way.</hi> (Witty Varlet!) <hi>They cannot ſing a Pſalm but they make his Confuſion the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of it:</hi> The Burden of a Pſalm is indeed a new expreſſion by which we may perceive our Author is deeply read in Ballad, and what does a man's Learning ſignify, if he may not have the liberty to ſhew it? But now according to the preparations for the raiſing of our expectation, we might imagine to find ſomething very extraordinary indeed; As how they met in large Congregations, and with one Heart and Voice Invoked the Fall and Ruin of this Cruel Perſecuter; How the whole Church kept Solemn, and at leaſt Weekly, Faſts to humble themſelves before the Throne of Mercy, that the Miſeries and grievous Sufferings they lay under, might in ſome meaſure of time be taken from 'em, But as I have obſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93598:15"/>
it is not the Method of this Worthy Author, to perform any thing that he would make us believe: The contents of his Chapters are high and threatning like the Huffings of Cowards; But his Chapters themſelves like the fighting of Cowards too as much at a diſtance from the point as is poſſible. But inſtead of all this, this Bankrupt-Brain'd Fellow when he has run into our debt almoſt a whole Hiſtory, would Compound with us for two ridiculous Stories of a Company of Mad Fellowes not unlike our Modern <hi>Muggletonians,</hi> and a fooliſh Old Woman that had made her ſelf Head of a Female Conſort of ſweet Singers. The Stories run thus: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>46th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Julian</hi> having given the Chriſtians Leave to remove the Bones of one <hi>Babylas</hi> a Martyr from the place where <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Temple ſtood: The People that ſetched the Coſſin went dancing before it and ſinging <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, repeating after every Verſe, <hi>Confounded be all they that Worſhip graven Images;</hi> Upon which <hi>Julian</hi> Commanded the Leaders of this Dance to be apprehended. Now to examine the meaning of this a little,</p>
            <p>And we ſhall find it palpably no more, then a Libel upon the Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of theſe Chriſtians: for what can be gathered from hence, but that our Author intended to repreſent <hi>Julian</hi> a Merciful and Indulgent Prince, and one that proceeded much rather like a Cheriſher af Chriſtianity then a deſtroyer of it: for a Mercileſs, and Inhumane Perſecutor might have Commanded Miniſters of his Fury to have digg'd up the Carcaſs of the Martyr out of it's Quiet grave, and Expoſed it with Diſgrace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumely to the Birds of the Air, and the Beaſts of the Field, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Inſtead of this we find him here Commended to us as One that practized Methods much milder, and let the Chriſtians themſelves remove the reliques of their dead Brother, that all Decent and Pious Ceremony might be uſed in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it. Well, and how did the Chriſtians thank him for this Indulgence? Why (ſayes our Author) <hi>They wiſhed God Confound him for his pains:</hi> This is the true Expoſition of the Text, this is the plain Engliſh of the Story; and if this be not a Satyr againſt Chriſtianity, and a Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick upon the Apoſtate, I know not what can be.</p>
            <p>The other Story is this of an Old Woman, one Madam <hi>Publia,</hi> who had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>48th.</hi>
               </note> under her Command a Company of Virgins forſooth (now our Author may call this reverend Lady by what title he pleaſes, whether a Lady Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs or Mother of the Maids, no matter, but an old Woman's keeping a Company of Virgins will bear a great many Interpretations.) Well, but in ſhort, according to <hi>Theodoret,</hi> this ancient Gentlewoman, and her Young Ladies were alwayes ſinging Praiſes to God, that's certain; but when the Emperour paſſed by, they ſung their Pſalms the louder, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him fit to be deſpiſed and derided: now which the relative <hi>Him,</hi> here relates to, whether God or the Emperour (for ought I can gueſs by his Writings,) may puzzle a Better Graecian or Grammarian than our Author to determine: and if ſo, the old Woman for all this may be a very wicked old Woman. But to make the beſt of the caſe, it ſeems as often as <hi>Julian</hi> paſſed by they Left off the devotion of ſinging meekly to the Praiſes of their Creator, and fell a roaring and bawling to affront and provoke the Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93598:15"/>
This ſeems not very unlike a Neſt of Hornets that hum and buzz migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Muſically while they are buſie with their harmleſs honey; but if any thing paſs by, though it never diſturb e'm, they encreaſe their notes to a hideous cry, and all ſwarm out to ſting and vex it: Though for the credit of her Profeſſion, I hope this old Womans Ladies were not every way like Hornets; that is, I hope they had no ſtings in their Tayls, how ſharp ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their Tongues were. But to return to the matter. What return did <hi>Julian</hi> make for theſe Indignities?</p>
            <p>Why as to the firſt: A Leader of the Dance, One <hi>Theodorus,</hi> being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and put to rack; (and here we have our true Proteſtant Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor clenching his Nayl with a Popiſh Miracle) being asked <hi>if he felt any pain?</hi> anſwered, <hi>he felt a little:</hi> but there ſtood by him a certain Youth, who all the while wiped off his ſweat with a very white linnen cloath, and often poured cold water upon him which ſo delighted him, that he was ſorry when he was taken off from the Rack; <hi>Quis haec recitando, temperet à Riſu?</hi> Now all I ſay to this is, that one Miracle may be as good as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and if this be true, I know not why we ſhould doubt of St. <hi>Dennis</hi>'s Carrying his head ſo far as it is ſaid he did after it was cut quite off; or a great many others which (when ever they fit his humour of ſcribling) I ſuppoſe our Author won't boggle at delivering for Orthodox, for all his Compariſon between Popery and Paganiſm.</p>
            <p>As for Old Mrs. <hi>Publia</hi> when ſhe received chaſtiſement for her inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the Emperour, <hi>Odds fiſh ſhe ſhew'd her ſelf a Woman of ſpirit, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>49th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>gave him as good as he brought, ay marry did ſhe; ſhe ſhot at him,</hi> ſayes our Author: Well, but how did ſhe ſhoot at him? <hi>why, ſhe ply'd him with her ſmall ſhot of Spiritual Songs, as ſhe us'd to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is a very hopeful account of our Author's Fifth Chapter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Devotions of the Chriſtians; namely, how a few Mad-men and an Old Woman turned the Praiſes of God into Curſes upon the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: For which indeed we are told a Story of one <hi>Theodorus</hi>'s being rack't for it, but with a Popiſh Lye tack't to the end of it, that we might be ſure not to believe it; for it is the only inſtance of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Cruelty we have hitherto met with through the whole Book; and our Author had ſpoyl'd his main <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> The Apology for his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtare.</note> deſign, if he had not ſeaſoned it with an improbability which he was morally certain no body could give credit to.</p>
            <p>And thus in the next place we ſhall ſurvey his Sixth Chapter, and what he ſayes concerning their Prayers and Tears.</p>
            <p>And truly upon the ſtricteſt Enquiry I could make, I cannot find that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>52d.</hi>
               </note> he ſayes any thing of them at all. He recites indeed ſeveral fragments of Devotions penned in the Plural number, as if they had been the Prayers of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>53d.</hi>
               </note> Congregations; but tells us afterwards how <hi>Gregory</hi> ſayes <hi>they were his former Thoughts and Cryes to God: So that</hi> (ſayes our Author himſelf) <hi>it is poſſible they were his own private Devotions:</hi> but concludes however very Learnedly from thence, <hi>That it is evident the publick Devotions of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ran in the ſame ſtrain.</hi> Now how it is evident becauſe they were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93598:16"/>
               <hi>Gregory</hi>'s private Devotions, that therefore they muſt be the Publick Prayers of the Church too, I cannot for my heart diſcover: But the Scribler has all along a particular way of arguing which I perceive ſatisfies himſelf, how much ſoever in the dark it leaves his Readers. And all that I can find for my life that this Chapter amounts to, is, that it was thought to be much for old <hi>Gregory</hi>'s honour that he helpt to Pray <hi>Julian</hi> to death; whence all the concluſion I can raiſe is, That our Author has done his utmoſt to make <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>40th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Prayers no other then like the Enchantments of a Witch; for Praying People to death is at beſt but a holyer kind of Witchcraft; and if our Author thinks to bring that Practice into faſhion in theſe our dayes of Devotion, I would not give him nine pence for his Project; for I am confident the ſecret of it is Quite loſt, and irrecoverable; And dare ſwear (referring my ſelf, were it poſſible, to all the Bills of Mortality for theſe 600 Years and upwards) that there has not been one man Pray'd to death ſince the Conqueſt: This perhaps ſome men may think a bold Propoſition, but I'll ſtand to it. And more then that, upon examining the Seventh Chapter how <hi>Julian</hi> came by his End, I'l hold an even wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he was not Pray'd to death neither.</p>
            <p>For ſays our Author in the very firſt Paragraph of this Chapter, <hi>After</hi> Julian <hi>had Reigned about Nineteen Months being in</hi> Perſia, <hi>and his Army</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>56th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſuddenly attaqued by the Enemy, he made ſuch haſt from place to place to Relieve thoſe Troops which were moſt hotly Engaged, that he forgot his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; and while he thus expoſed himſelf, was ſtruck with a Horſeman's Spear which pierced his ſide, and ſtuck in the bottom of his Liver, of which Wound about Midnight he dyed.</hi> So that by this it is apparent he was not Prayed to death, whatever our Author was pleaſed to ſay before, but is very remarkable through the whole Book, that he generally has a way of changing his Opinion with his Chapter; neither do we find in any Hiſtories mention made that <hi>Julian</hi> vomited any crooked Pins or Needles, or Balls of hair before he dyed; which if old <hi>Gregory</hi> and Madam <hi>Publia</hi> had bewitched and pray'd him to death, he muſt certainly have done. Yet let not any one think that I too forcibly detort and wreſt the ſence of our Author here, for he ſayes himſelf <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>66th, That theſe Chriſtians ſometimes ſaid all their Prayers backward to fetch down Vengeance upon his head.</hi> Which according to the Opinion of Learned Writers upon that Subject, is a great part and ceremony uſed in the Enchantments of Witches. But are we ſure after all this, that <hi>Julian</hi> was killed by the Dart of a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian?</hi> No, for ſayes our Author, <hi>One</hi> Calliſtus <hi>who was then in</hi> Julian<hi>'s</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>59th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Service, and has given us the History of that War, ſayes it was a Daemon that did it.</hi> Now this I muſt Confeſs is apt to lead ones opinion back again, and make a man believe there was a little Incantation and Sorcery uſed in the buſineſs; but I am reſolved to the Contrary, and let our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor do his Worſt, he ſhall never root it in my faith, that two ſuch Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Primitive Chriſtians as Old <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazianzum,</hi> and <hi>Publia</hi> the Mother of an <hi>Antiochian</hi> Biſhop, would give their Souls to the Devil for the deſtruction of any Body. Beſides, the Prince of Darkneſs (our Author may know I believe) is a Politick Prince, and would not eaſily be wheadled withal to deſtroy one who was in a way of doing him ſuch Service, as <hi>Julian</hi> might have done, by utterly extirpating the Religion of Salvation, and giving Hell title to all the Souls of Mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93598:16"/>
In few words, as to this Chapter concerning <hi>Julian</hi>'s death, I defy any any body who is not otherwayes ſatisfy'd of the matter, to make any right judgment out of it what manner of death he dy'd, or whether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he ever dy'd at all: for firſt Mr. Author tells us he was killed by a Dart from a <hi>Perſian</hi> Horſeman; then he tells us that it was not a <hi>Perſian</hi> who did it, but a certain Devil <hi>incognito</hi> that rode Volunteer in the Army o' purpoſe: And laſt of all, to Confound and Entangle the matter utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, tells us, how one <hi>Libanius</hi> a Sophiſt Inſinuates in his Writings, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>60th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he who kill'd</hi> Julian <hi>was a Chriſtian.</hi> Now according to the common weight of reports, the main of the thing it ſelf, upon the whole matter may be a Lye: for commonly when we hear a Story delivered ſo many ſeveral wayes, we ſuſpend our belief, and give no credit to it in General, at all; ſo that for ought we know, <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate may be living to this very hour, nay Converſant (as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> once among the Beaſts,) with many worthy true Proteſtants and others here in <hi>England,</hi> where having forgot the paſt glories of his Empire, and contenting himſelf with the ſolitary pleaſures of <hi>Brandy</hi> and <hi>Mundungus,</hi> (ſtill preſerving his name) has Condeſcended to the humble office of tranſcribing and publiſhing dull Libels and Lampoons, for worſe fools to own, then the blockheads that make e'm.</p>
            <p>In the next place as to the uſage of <hi>Julian</hi>'s memory: this precious Author has thought Convenient to write a whole Chapter, how they (that is to ſay, by <hi>Gregory</hi> their repreſentative in an Invective) call'd him <hi>Herod,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page the 63d.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Judas, Traytor, Murderer,</hi> &amp;c. till after all, they Lodged him in Hell, and there they left him: which I ſay was very charitably done, and ſo fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel poor <hi>Julian:</hi> Only I muſt deſire to remind our Author of a mighty miſtake he has made in matter of truth; for whereas towards the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Book, <hi>page</hi> the <hi>14th,</hi> in the ſhort account of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Life, he ſayes that ſome of the Fathers write, <hi>that he would ſuffer no Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to teach;</hi> but make no mention at all of his forbidding the Youth to learn. In this <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> Chapter, and <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>56th,</hi> rather then loſe the credit of a Miracle, as he calls it, he makes bold to give all thoſe Fathers the Lye, and declares, <hi>That the News of</hi> Julian<hi>'s Death was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page the 56th,</hi> and <hi>57th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to ſome of the Chriſtians by Miracle; for there was a Chriſtian School-Maſter at that time at</hi> Antioch, <hi>and he being asked in deriſion what the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter's Son was doing, being, fill'd with Divine Grace,</hi> ſayes our Author, <note place="margin">Another Popiſh Miracle of our true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Authors.</note> 
               <hi>reply'd, He is making a Coffin.</hi> A very heavenly Speech, truly: and the School-Maſter was a Wagg I'l warrant him, as well as a School-Maſter.</p>
            <p>This is the Sum total of the Account our Author has given us of the Sence of the Primitive Chriſtians about <hi>Julian</hi>'s Succeſſion, and their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour towards him; where I think it is ſufficiently Evident, That his whole drift and deſign has been (as much as in him lay) to ſtrike at the very root of Chriſtianity, by expoſing the weakneſs, falſe dealing, and ingratitude of a few intemperate Zealots, under the name and title of <hi>Primitive Chriſtians:</hi> and cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ging other principal Members of the Church, at that time, with no leſs Crimes then <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> and <hi>Murder;</hi> While <hi>Julian</hi> all along, is repreſented the moſt Indulgent, forbearing, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and patient Prince, that ever wink't and turned aſide at the Effron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93598:17"/>
Inſolencies of an unruly people whom his heart pity'd; and that this was his drift, will more largely appear in the following Chapter, Being our Authors own reflexions upon the behaviour of theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: and here indeed (ſpeaking for himſelf, and not having occaſion to Quote <hi>Gregory</hi> fo often,) we may more particularly diſtinguiſh the ſpirit of the Man; for he cannot help ſhewing us his thoughts fairly and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>65th.</hi>
               </note> clearly upon the matter; but ſayes in the very firſt line of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (and ſo onward for a whole leaf together, which I ſhall epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize as well as I can,) That <hi>Julian</hi>'s perſecution was but a Flea-biting to what the Chriſtians formerly had felt, that the caſe of the diſcard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed School-maſters, Phyſitians, and Souldiers, was the greateſt ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all <hi>Julian</hi>'s Edicts: that <hi>Julian,</hi> to ſpeak properly, was rather a Tempter then a Perſecutor; and one who wrought upon Mens Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs &amp; Ambition more then their fear; and that whatſoever he ever deſigned againſt the Chriſtians, was far ſhort of what other Emperors had executed. Is not this an Apology for <hi>Julian</hi> now! is not this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>66th.</hi>
               </note> him the moſt equally dealing and Indulgent Prince that ever reigned<hi>!</hi> if the Reader is not ſo ſatisfy'd, let him but carry his Eyes a very little farther, and obſerve how he treats and juſtifies thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and their proceedings. <hi>For yet</hi> ſayes he, (notwithſtanding all this) <hi>how do the Chriſtians Treat this Emperor!</hi> One would take them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> Ib.</note> to be the Apoſtates, one while reproaching him, ruffling with him, and vexing every vein in his Royal heart; another while ſaying all their Prayers backward, and calling down vengeance upon his head; After that, dancing and leaping for joy at his death, and inſulting over his memory: but for the name of Chriſtians, he had better have fallen amongſt <hi>Barbarians,</hi> And yet (ſayes our Author farther) <hi>he often would mildly put them in mind of their chriſtianity too:</hi> But they call him by the bloodieſt names of the Devil, for taking advantages of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine in this particular, which ſayes, <hi>we muſt not avenge our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>67th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſelves, nor render evil for evil, &amp;c.</hi> Now let any unprejudiced Readers but peruſe theſe two Characters ſeriouſly <hi>(Viz.</hi> that firſt of <hi>Julian,</hi> and this after it of the Chriſtians) and thence Judge who ſet this noble Author to work, and the cauſe he writes for, Judge which he has done the beſt ſervice to, by the feats of his triumphing Pen; whether Chriſtianity or Apoſtacy, God or the Devil.</p>
            <p>Nor ought his telling us, that <hi>chriſtianity was then the Eſtabliſhed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the Empire,</hi> at all, to prevail upon our belief, till he bring better Arguments for it then thoſe I before obſerved, of the mighty number of Seven Thouſand, that did not bow the Knee to <hi>Baal:</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity was indeed a Tolerated Religion of the Empire, increaſed and got ſtrength under the Patronage and Protection of thoſe Chriſtian Emperors before <hi>Julian:</hi> but that it was ever Conſtituted or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by their Laws, to be receiv'd as the univerſal Religion of their Dominions, is a ſecret, which I am afraid our Author's Learning will hardly yet a while, from any Hiſtories diſcover to the World. For though thoſe Emperors were Chriſtians themſelves, we do not find, (from any thing at leaſt that our Author informs us except we will take his own bare word for the matter) that they ever began a general
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93598:17"/>
tirpation of Heatheniſm, or Commanded univerſal Baptiſm over all their World<hi>:</hi> They made no Laws for bringing Nations under the ſame Diſcipline of one Chriſtian Church, which had it been a Religion eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law, muſt and would certainly have been done<hi>:</hi> But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were, or were not, ſignifies little, or nothing to my preſent purpoſe, it being only my deſign in theſe Remarques, to let the World ſee, how falſely they are dealt withal by a Scribler, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to write a Satyr upon an Apoſtate, when he has taken all the care that's poſſible, to vindicate and defend him<hi>:</hi> which as he has done ſufficiently in contradicting the truth, ſo has he been as Induſtrious for it in contadicting himſelf too<hi>:</hi> for when he comes, as he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>71ſt.</hi>
               </note> calls it, to ſumm up all in a word, he tells us, <hi>that the firſt Chriſtians ſuffered indeed according to the Laws of their Country; whereas thoſe under</hi> Julian <hi>were perſecuted contrary to Law,</hi> who did not fairly enact ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Laws againſt them, but put them to death upon <hi>Shams</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Crimcs.</hi> Now how this agrees with what our Author told us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in Page the <hi>66th,</hi> let the Reader look back, and he will ſoon be ſatisfied: for there he tells us <hi>Julian</hi>'s perſecution was but a <hi>Flea-biting</hi> to what the Chriſtians formerly felt; That he good man wrought upon mens <hi>covetouſneſs</hi> more then their <hi>fear:</hi> yet here, Page the <hi>71ſt</hi> he was a <hi>Cruel Murderer</hi> and <hi>putter to death.</hi> Nay upon <hi>pretended Crimes</hi> too, what credit ought to be given to ſo impudent a Fellow as this, who will rather give himſelf the Lye, then uſe the memory of an Enemy to God, and a reviler of his Bleſſed Son, as it deſerves<hi>!</hi> yet this is he whom a true Proteſtant party (as they call themſelves) cry up for a Libel writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt their Chriſtianity; and a moſt Religious Zealous Pious Lord has choſen for his Chaplain.</p>
            <p>And theſe indeed are the reflections of our Author upon the behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the Chriſtians againſt <hi>Julian;</hi> with this Title had he charged his dreadful Murdering piece of all the Ninth Chapter. But finding that it would not go off ſo, has primed it with a new one of paſſive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which may more properly be called, an Appendix to his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face: for it is a ſolution of the caſe, how far we ought to be obedient to a Popiſh Prince.</p>
            <p>Now though it be palpable enough at what head he Aims his odious Title; And though I own my ſelf a naturally devoted Servant, to that Illuſtrious Heroick Virtuous Sufferer, whom I never could be convinced (by any proof or the ſtrickeſt enquiry I could yet make, (barring pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſuſpicion) deſerved that denomination<hi>:</hi> yet here, Abſtracting the caſe from the Perſon, I am contented for once to take the frivolous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in hand, as this trifling Author has ſtated it, and ſee what dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage according to his Arguments, are likely to accrue from a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prince, (granting there could be ſuch a thing) to the Eſtabliſhed Religion of theſe Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>After which (allowing the eſteem our Authors party have for the ſervice he has done them) if it appear from his own Arguments to the contrary, that our Religion, according to its Eſtabliſhment, in its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93598:18"/>
perfect purity of doctrine, and it's outward defence and bulwark of the Law, be ſo confirmed, that (if it forſake not its own ſtrength) nothing at home can ſhake or diſturb it, much leſs perſecute it: I think it were but Reaſon, (if Peace and Truth, (according to their pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) be the things they ſo much labour for:) that they henceforth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into the Arms of the Church, the obedience to the Law, renounce their Phariſaical pride of ſeparation, and let the People of <hi>England</hi> be once more fellow Chriſtians and fellow Subjects.</p>
            <p>If then (as our Author ſays, Page 73d.) <hi>We have our Religion ſettled by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>73d.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſuch Laws as cannot be altered without our own Conſent,</hi> what need he in the next page have asked the fooliſh Queſtion, <hi>Whether or no we are to go to Maſs to Morrow or have our Throats out?</hi> If, as he ſays, there can be no <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>75th.</hi>
               </note> need of paſſive obedience for our Religion, but by our own Treachery to it, in parting with thoſe good Laws which protect it, and in agreeing to ſuch as ſhall deſtroy it; why all theſe noiſes and clamors? why theſe alarums a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us? why theſe outcries of approaching Perſecution and imminent Popery? If the Laws of the Kingdom abſolutely and entirely tend (as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they do) to the maintenance of the eſtabliſhed Church, and the rooting out the Superſtitious Religion of <hi>Rome,</hi> and if there be no power in <hi>England</hi> Civil or Military, but what meerly depends upon the Authority of thoſe Laws, and cannot move without it, where are thoſe dangers we ſo fooliſhly affright our ſelves withall? or whence can they ariſe? From within our ſelves I am ſure they cannot, except Popery be to grow upon us out of the Earth, like Muſhrooms in a Night, or gather over our heads like a thick Cloud in the Air, and rain down a ſhower of Armed Papiſts in ready Rank and File, to over-run and deſtroy us er'e we can think of our defence.</p>
            <p>Popiſh black bills, 'tis true, have been ſent to a Rendezvous by the Poſt, but never more heard of: An Army of Pilgrims too were Landed, but to no purpoſe neither; Yet theſe things were in a time, when we had a dangerous Plot ready to diſcharge it ſelf among us, but now the Pay-Maſter of the Imaginary Army to be raiſed for the uſe of that Plot, is gone into another World, the reſt of the Principal Officers under a cloſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and like to lie there; Nay all their Commiſſions loſt too, and not ſomuch as one Cypher of Father <hi>Oliva</hi>'s to ſhew for the bus'neſs; What grounds are there for our Fears now? Are not all the Popiſh Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Kingdom excluded from their Votes in the Houſe of Lords? Or can any Man be a Member of the Lower Houſe who does not take the Oaths of Allegiance, Supremacy, Teſt, and Sacrament according to the Church of <hi>England?</hi> And are not theſe Two Houſes the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the Kingdom, who are to prepare by Votes all manner of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for the preſervation of our Safety and Religion, and Confirmation of our Rights, to be paſſed into Laws by the Royal Aſſent? And can there in a Government and Church thus Eſtabliſhed, thus Fortified, be fears of Popery or Perſecution from it ſelf! No, were there but another <hi>Teſt</hi> to paſs through the Kingdom againſt Separation and Schiſm, as there is againſt Popery, I think then even our own Treachery to our Religion were impoſſible to be ſuppoſed, in parting with thoſe good Lawes which ſhould protect it: I believe then the <hi>35th</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> would no more be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93598:18"/>
ſtruck at, but put in due Execution; Rebels, and Mutineers reduced and made obedient to the Government and Laws; Mechanicks kept to their Shops, and not ſuffered to turn their Ware-houſes into Nurſeries of falſe Doctrine, Prophaneneſs, Blaſphemy and Rebellion. And ſince as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſays, <hi>it would be Treachery to part with thoſe good Lawes which protect our Religion,</hi> They who would Aboliſh this Law are not, 'tis to be feared, ſo true Sons of the Church as they ought to be, by Leaving ſo wide a gap for all manner of Confuſion to enter in at, and rend the peaceful Bowels of their Mother. No, Let us baniſh thoſe needleſs Fears, that ſerve for nothing but to perplex the ſweeteſt Peace, that ever a happy Nation was bleſt withal; and avoid thoſe Enemies of our Proſperity that would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote them. Let all true Sons of the Eſtabliſhed Church reſolve by Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to their Prince, Obedience to his Authority, Mutual Love, Charity, and entire Union, amongſt and towards one another; to maintain, and defend it: reſolve to ſtand by and preſerve the Laws that ſupport it, from the annoyance both of its right, and left-hand Enemies; let us reſolve this and be Quiet: and if we do ſo, we ſhall be Quiet, to the Confuſion of our Author, and thoſe miſchievous creeping Caterpillars his Party.</p>
            <p>Nay ſince there are good Laws for the protecting of our Religion againſt its Enemies, the Schiſmatical Phanaticks, as well as Papiſts and Others; the beſt way certainly of protecting it, is, by putting thoſe good Lawes in Execution, nay to the utmoſt Extent, and improvement of them if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: and for this too, (to give our Author one Quotation for his whole Book-ful) let <hi>Bracton</hi> be my ſecurity, Nay the very place too where Mr. Deacon is pleaſed to Quote him himſelf upon this occaſion: <hi>(viz. Libro</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.) in theſe words; <hi>Leges cum fuerint approbatae conſenſu utentium, et Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento Regum Confirmatae, Mutari non poſſunt, nec deſtrui, ſine communi conſenſu &amp; conſilio eorum omnia, Quorum Conſilio &amp; conſenſu fuerunt promulgatae. That is to ſay, that ſince the Laws have been approved by the conſent of thoſe for whoſe uſe and benefit they were made, and Confirmed by our Kings; They cannot be changed, nor deſtroyed, without the Common conſent and advice of all thoſe, by whoſe Advice and Conſent they were firſt ſet forth:</hi> So far our Author. But had he pleaſed to have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his Eye a line farther, he might have found this added; <hi>Quod in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liùs tamen converti poſſunt, etiam ſine eorum Conſenſu, Quia non deſtruitur quod in melius Commutatur;</hi> i. e. <hi>That for all this, nevertheleſs they may be improved at the diſcretion of the Prince, even without ſuch Conſent, ſince no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſaid to be deſtroyed, which is changed for the better.</hi> Which all makes good my aforementioned Aſſertion, That for the preſervation of our Religion, the Laws ought to be put in Execution, with the utmoſt Rigor, and (when the King ſhall think fitting) in ſo good a Cauſe, they ought, if poſſible, to be ſtretched and improved too: For Laws being the Inſtruments, put into the hands and power of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing, wherewith to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern and Protect his People; thoſe Inſtruments are to be uſed at his own diſcretion certainly; And a good Father of his Country cannot but think himſelf obliged, to give them their utmoſt and ſevereſt reach for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and reducing of Contumacious ſtubborn impudent Mutineers and Rebels; as well as ſometimes in Goodneſs to abate their Rigor, when he finds an object that may deſerve his Mercy.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93598:19"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93598:19"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93598:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93598:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93598:21"/>
Our Author might have found out this as well as I now: But I ſuppoſe he may be one of thoſe that are for clipping the King's Prerogative, and for that end would ſerve all thoſe Authors ſo too that defend and aſſert it. And indeed I obſerve in all their Writings, that it is much the practice of the Advocates for that Party, (whenever they have an Occaſion to ſhew their Reading, &amp; Quote a poor Author that never intended them any Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,) to ſnip, pare and ſhave him down juſt to their purpoſe, ſo clap him upon the Margent of their Pamphlet, in hopes to Cobble up their falſe Arguments with defaced and mangled truth, and make them paſs for Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Doctrine.</p>
            <p>And indeed I cannot tell all along what to make of this giddy-headed Author I am to handle: He turns, and ſhifts, and dodges, and never keeps one Courſe: He pretends to treat of paſſive Obedience, but never tells us what paſſive Obedience is: diſcourſes from no principle in the world; nor gives us any definition of his Theam: and indeed upon due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration it were unreaſonable to expect it of him, for had he ever read Ethicks, he would have learned more honeſty then to have publiſhed ſuch a Book He firſt tells us in a word, <hi>That we are ſecured ſo well by our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>75th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Laws, that paſſive Obedience muſt (except by our own treachery) be for ever unpracticable amongst us:</hi> yet waſts Twenty or Thirty Pages more to ſcare us with the dangers of its doctrine, which he ſayes, <hi>'Tis true can never</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>78th.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>diſcover its malignity under his Majeſties gracious Reign, which God prolong and proſper, who has been pleaſed to give the Nation the ſecurity of his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oath, &amp;c. But in caſe we ſhould fall under a Popiſh Succeſſor, then this Bloody Doctrine will have the Opportunity to ſhew its ſelf in its own Colours, and we may then ſee, and it may be feel the ſting of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here really it is very hard to forbear laughing moſt outragiouſly at this Fellow and his Canting, but that I correct and keep my ſpleen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in a pure principle of charity, for fear leſt I miſtake his frenzy for his folly. <hi>The King has been pleaſed to give us the ſecurity of his Coronation Oath,</hi> Quotha! <hi>but in caſe we ſhould fall under a Popiſh Succeſſor!—</hi>Well, what then? Muſt not he give us the Security of his Coronation Oath too? Yes, my dear Author, that he muſt, and I believe Thou mayſt be ſatisfied it will be his Intereſt to keep it too, except thou canſt think him ſo blind to his own good, as to hazard the involving of his Nation in blood, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and endangering of his Throne for ever, and all for the great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage he may propoſe to himſelf, of bringing in the Power of a Tyrannical Clergy, to Impoveriſh his People, leſſen his Revenues, and weaken his Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh but</hi> (ſays our Author) <hi>I ſuppoſe that a Popiſh Succeſſor being in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſo a lawful Magiſtrate, will perſecute Proteſtants.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>79th.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer; I deſire to know, which way he will perſecute Proteſtants: will he perſecute them with the Laws? No. They are of the Proteſtant ſide. If he will raiſe a Popiſh Army and bring in Popery with Drum and Trumpet, I humbly deſire to know where he will beat up his Drums for them, and how the Popiſh Officers will make their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93598:21"/>
in the Countrey when they are to raiſe them: or what Popiſh Towns will give 'em Quarters till they come to their Rendezvous: Or which way this Popiſh Succeſſor will get a Popiſh Parliament, to give him Proteſtant Money, to pay this Popiſh Army: all theſe things will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: For let the Romiſh Religion be never ſo much in the matter, your Muſqueteers and Pikemen will have a certain Proteſtant principle of <hi>point d' Argent, point de Swiſſe:</hi> Though after all it would be a damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſurpriſe at laſt, if our Author ſhould have a Project at the end of all this, to conceal his Politicks till this Popiſh Succeſſor Comes, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelf to his Privy Council by a trick he has in the bottom of his Budget, for the bringing in Popery in a peaceable way, and enſlaving the Nation without a farthings Coſt or a moments trouble: that I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs would be ſomething new, and not unpretty. <hi>Marry but</hi> (ſayes the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> Ib.</note> Gentleman farther) <hi>if he does not perſecute Hereticks with fire and ſword, he lyes at the Popes Mercy to have his Kingdom taken away from him:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Mr. Author, and that's a very weighty Conſideration; But do you think in your Conſcience that he will part with it ſo! Truly a deep fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight into politick Conſequences is a great bleſſing to one that is to write much upon <hi>Suppoſes;</hi> Though if a man might be ſo bold as to put in a word with you, really it ſeems unto me, (Noble Sir <hi>Poll.)</hi> that you do pleaſe to ſpeak of more then need be done: for if you dare to Engage this Popiſh Succeſſor (after you have eſtabliſhed your Intereſt by your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject from bringing in his Religion) to let us poor Proteſtants live in Peace and Quietneſs, as I believe you may; I'l Engage the Pope ſhall be very favourable to him, and for a very ſmall Quit-Rent let him keep the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold of his Kingdom: Bleſs us, how things will be managed when the Reader of <hi>Covent Garden</hi> comes to be a primiere Miniſter, and I Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour Extraordinary to his Holineſs! but till that time comes I can foreſee no fear of a Popiſh Perſecution, nor very great danger of the Popes diſpoſing of theſe Three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Well, but what are we to think now, if, as our Author ſayes, into the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> Ib.</note> bargain, <hi>that beſides the danger of being dethroned by the Pope if he does not perſecute Proteſtants, he runs alſo the hazard of being ſerved as the Two</hi> Henry<hi>'s of</hi> France <hi>were?</hi> Why truly nothing is Impoſſible: but we hope it is not altogether ſo probable, that a King ſhould be ſtabb'd in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Country, for not perſecuting its Religion: let him keep the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church from hurting the Proteſtants, and certainly the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants will be able to keep their Enemies from hurting of him; or the Pope from taking away his Kingdom either: 100000 Proteſtants will be too hard for all the Pope's Bulls in Chriſtendom. This Policy I believe Any Succeſſor (let his private Perſwaſion be what it will) may find very neceſſary in <hi>England,</hi> and Twenty to One be wiſe enough to practiſe it too: for <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> it is very obſervable, was not Kill'd by <hi>Ravillac</hi> till he left the Proteſtant Religion, and encouraged Popery; had he kept it under ſtill, and Eſtabliſh'd the Reformed above it, it is an even wager but he might have dy'd in his Bed, and been gather'd to his Fathers in Peace. Beſides, it is not abſurd to imagine, that it was not ſo much an Eccleſiaſtical as a Temporal Policy, which ſent the Villanous Dagger to that Brave Prince's Heart.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93598:22"/>
But our Author has indeed a moſt extraordinary Rule of Policy of his own, and we may perceive it plainly enough by that which follows: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Let things fall as they will, though ſome perſons may be ſo happy as to think he will not perſecute, yet every body muſt grant that he may perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, that the thing is Poſſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from this hour, Thou moſt Confounded Author, do I declare Immortal enmity with thee; nor will ever be Ambaſſadour to the Pope, nor ſhalt thou be ever a Miniſter of State. It is poſſible in the Devil's name that a Popiſh Succeſſor may perſecute! And is this the Mouſe that thy Mountain of a Book has brought forth at laſt? and ought a Bill of Excluſion to paſs for this, becauſe Thou ſay'ſt <hi>it is poſſible that a Popiſh Succeſſor may perſecute?</hi> hadſt Thou ſtuck to thy firſt Argument, <hi>That our Religion can never be in a condition of Perſecution, but by our own Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery to it, in parting with thoſe good Laws which protect it, and in agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch as ſhall deſtroy it;</hi> hadſt Thou kept to that Foundation, thou mighteſt indeed have raiſed ſome diſcourſe of Reaſon: but that the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility that an evil may happen, is ſufficient for any reaſonable men to raiſe their fears of it upon; or a lawful cauſe to uſe unnatural and unequal means to prevent it, is an opinion I would gladly ſee thee put in practice; It is not impoſſible, but that thou mayeſt come to be a Slave in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys one day, and compelled to live a wretched painful life for ſeveral mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable years together: why doſt thou not generouſly hang thy ſelf for a remedy againſt it<hi>!</hi> for ſuch an accident may happen to thee, the thing is poſſible. Or if ſince it is poſſible that a Popiſh Succeſſor may perſecute, that it would be therefore juſt and reaſonable to exclude him, why thou vile blunderer, it is poſſible too (if that be all) that a Proteſtant Succeſſor may perſecute as well as a Popiſh one: that a Proteſtant Succeſſor may turn Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt: it is poſſible that the beſt Prince may change his Nature and turn a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, neither of theſe accidents but are poſſible in Nature, &amp; ſo by thy Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all Heirs to the Crown ought to be therefore Excluded, and no more Kings reign over us becauſe 'tis poſſible they may one way or other prove perſecutors: &amp; I am very much afraid indeed that's the vile falſe conſequence thou wouldeſt diſpute for: But to come cloſer to thee in thy rule of poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, it is not impoſſible but that ſuch a Parliament may come as to Vote a Bill for the rooting out of our Religion, and Eſtabliſhing Popery or a Worſe in its place: were it therefore reaſonable to paſs a Law that never any more Parliaments ſhould Sit in <hi>England,</hi> nay as thou haſt ſtated it, it really carries the more ſpecious pretence of danger of the two: for it being impoſſible, that our Religion in its lawful Eſtabliſhment, can be peaceably altered, (if any way) by any other means then an Act of Parliament; the King too being but one man, and the Parliament many, it is more reaſonable that the opinions of the many, ſhould ſway the will or inclination of one, then that the will of one ſhould over-rule the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and inclinations of the many: ſince therefore it is impoſſible, that any Succeſſor can lawfully violate the Proteſtant Religion, but by the concurrence and conſent of a Parliament; All thy Argument amounts to, is, Take away Parliaments, and our Religion in law is ſafe. For ever the Nation is beholding to thee for thy parts: and by the ſervice thou art fit to do the State by thy Policy, we may gueſs what the Church may hope from thy Divinity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93598:22"/>
Well, but after all ſayes our Author, <hi>Since it is poſſible that a Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor may perſecute, it is even high time that we look about us, and ſee what we have to truſt to. The Goſpel doth not ſo much as allow any means when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape by Flight, betwixt denying and dying for the Earth: Well, but by what Law muſt we dye? By none,</hi> ſayes our Author, <hi>that I know, but Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, Sycophants and Murderers may.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I dare venture to hold this Author of ours Fifty pound to a ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that amongſt all his Noble acquaintaince, there is not one Paraſite, Sycopham, or Murderer, that knows any more Law for it, then he does himſelf. But Rhetorick is a fine thing, and a man that has the gift of it, can no more ſtop a Trope when its coming, then a <hi>Dutchman</hi> a belch; 'tis a great caſe now and then to a writer, and ought to be allowed him.</p>
            <p>But now I muſt beg leave to be a little more ſerious with my worthy Author, and take him to task with a ſevere ſcrutiny. <hi>What have we here,</hi> Page the 82d<hi>! There is no Authority upon Earth above the Law!</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>82d.</hi>
               </note> If our Author means by this, that the King is ſubject to the Law, I know not what they may amount to; and think it were but fit that he ſhould explain himſelf. But to take the words in their bare, and unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced ſignification: I ſay there is an Authority in the King, which is an Authority above the Law: And I think too it will be eaſie naturally to prove it. For whatſoever derives it's vertue from another Authority, is Inferiour to that Authority whence it is derived; and therefore the Law being the Kings Creature, made and informed with that force which it bears, by the Kings proper <hi>Fiat,</hi> and Royal Stamp: the Authority of ſuch a Law is but derivative, a Child begotten by the parent power natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urally in the King, and conſequently inferiour and ſubject to that firſt power, as much as a Child is naturally to a Father. Beſides the Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as I ſaid before) no other then an Inſtrument in the hands of the King, wherewith he is to govern and protect his people; certainly the weapon is not equal to the Arm that weilds it. For as a Sword is but a dead thing of its ſelf, its edge and point of no uſe at all, but as it is enforced and directed by the hand of him that bears it: ſo equally the Law, can exerciſe no Authority meerly of it ſelf at all, but as it is managed and put in motion, by the preeminent and ſuperintendent power in the King: ſo that there is certainly an orignal Fountain of Natural Authority in the King, above the mechanical inſtrumental Authority of the Laws.</p>
            <p>Nor will it be ſufficient that our Author Quotes <hi>Bracton</hi>'s Opinion in the caſe, to make his Argument irrefragable at all; For though <hi>Bracton</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>83d.</hi>
               </note> indeed was a very good Lawyer, we are not by any means to allow him infallible: eſpecially in a caſe which is evidently falſe. For whereas he ſayes indeed (as our Author hath cited him) that <hi>Rex debet eſſe ſub lege Quia lex facit Regem,</hi> I cannot by any means allow of his Propoſition; ſince the Law does not make the King, but the King the Laws. For if we look back to the original power of our Kings, as it is derived from the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt, we ſhall find that Conquerour was not made King
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93598:23"/>
by the Law, but by the Sword; nay after he had Vanquiſhed us, impoſed too his own <hi>Norman</hi> Laws in a great meaſure upon us: as is ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable from the abſolete <hi>French</hi> Language which they are to this day writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in. So that <hi>Bracton</hi> is in the wrong to ſay the Law makes the King, for the Race of our preſent Monarch is derived from that very Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who cut out his way to his Throne with his Sword, and by that Power ſet up ſuch Laws, as he himſelf thought ſitting; and what Laws have paſſed ſince, have been made Laws by the ſucceeding Kings after him, and not the Kings made by the Laws. For our Kings reign, and hold their Crowns by the right of that Conqueſt ſtill, which cannot be altered till they themſelves willingly reſign it, and take up a new Royalty upon new Conditions, and then indeed (as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſayes) <hi>The Law may make the King, and the King ought to be under the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet this does not hinder, but that (as our Author ſayes) Page the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>84th.</hi>
               </note> 84th, <hi>a Popiſh Succeſſor can have no Authority to exerciſe any illegal cruelty upon Proteſtants.</hi> And if ſo, certainly there is therefore much the leſs fear of him: By much leſs therefore ought we wilfully to rend and tear the preſent happineſs we now may live in, and be bleſt withal; by ſeperating our ſelves into unreaſonable Factions, for fear of a danger which is but wildly poſſible, and (in all conſideration of our preſent condition as we are fenced and defended by the beſt conſtituted Laws in the World, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept our own Treachery or folly deſtroy them) utterly improbable: for if (as our Author ſayes after) that bad Princes are hardly ever known to ſtoop ſo low as to be Executioners themſelves of their own cruelty; if we are out of our pain (as he ſayes) as to that difficulty, I cannot by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>85th.</hi>
               </note> any means admit of his ſecond ſcruple, that under a Popiſh Succeſſor the lives of all Proteſtants ſhall lye at the mercy of every Juſtice of Peace, Conſtable, or Tything-man, who ſhall have Catholick Zeal enough to deſtroy them. For this my dear <hi>Poll</hi> is filthy prevaricating: let us ſtill keep our ground, and be true to our Laws, this of all abſurdities is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to happen. For the Law has provided, that no man ſhall hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth bear any of thoſe offices, but approved and known Proteſtants, ſuch as muſt take the Sacrament, Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, and the Teſt to enable them for their employments, and till thoſe good preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Laws are abrogated by our own Treachery, it is in our own choice to be as happy as we would be, even under the very reign of a Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor.</p>
            <p>And whereas our Author (to ſhew what a Couragious Author he is) rouſes himſelf, and ſetting his Arms a Cymbo, cryes, Page the 87th, <hi>That though we cannot hinder Papiſts from being Idolaters. we will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to keep them from being our Murderers:</hi> I muſt beg leave to tell him as a friend, he might have ſpared his Breath, to cool his Pottage; for the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>88th.</hi>
               </note> Laws will do that buſineſs well enough, without his help. Nor can there be any <hi>petty Popiſh Officers</hi> (as he does his weak endeavour malitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſinuate) <hi>under a Popiſh Succeſſor, to be abſolute Emperors, and have the power of life and death;</hi> for as I obſerved before, the Law has taken care, that no Papiſt ſhall henceforth bear Office in this Kingdom; And this Scribler, before he had entangled himſelf in this Argument,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93598:23"/>
ſhould have found out a flaw where our Laws were lyable to be inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and broken, if he intended to have perſwaded us we were not ſafe under their ſhelter. In ſhort I am weary of moyling in the heavy road of his Nonſence; long to get rid of him and ſhake my ſelf clean: leaſt by farther endeavouring <hi>to anſwer a Fool according to his folly, I become like unto him.</hi> For he pretends to write Hiſtory, which he is able to bring to no definite Concluſion: and ſtrains at a diſcourſe, yet lays us down no principles. Sometimes indeed he has a great diſpoſition to a jeſt: but performs it as Awkardly, as I have ſeen a <hi>Jack-pudding</hi> ſhew feats of Activity: who when you would think his heels were charged with a miracle, comes ſquobb upon his breech, and looks like the Author of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian the Apoſtate.</hi> And thus I have done with this Ninth Chapter, being Reflections upon the Behaviour of his Primitive Arrian Chriſtians, and his opinion of paſſive Obedience.</p>
            <p>And now his next Chapter being, as he ſtyles it, <hi>a Compariſon of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Paganiſm:</hi> If the Reader expect I ſhould ſay any thing to that, I muſt fairly tell him the truth. I was ſo worryed with the foregoing part of the Book, that I could find in my heart to read but two leaves of it: wherein if our Author would reſolve me two ſcruples, I ſhould take it as a favour firſt; That whereas he ſayes, Page the 100, That Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> ſaid the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was a <hi>Babilonical Beaſt, and Whore, a deviliſh Drab, and a stinking Strumpet:</hi> I deſire to be ſatisfied how the Reverend Father came to know, whether a Strumpet ſtunk or no: Secondly, That he having Quoted part of a Homily in the next page to prove, that <hi>the Scripture calls the Romiſh Church a harlot,</hi> I humbly beg to be ſatisfy'd, how ſhe could be <hi>harlot</hi> when the Scripture was written, and when yet it is evident ſhe had not loſt her maiden-head?</p>
            <p>But whether he has done Paganiſm right, or Popery wrong in this Chapter, is not my buſineſs to Examine: who am not concerned for the honor of either of them, being born and educated in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as it is Eſtabliſhed by Law, and in that Church hope to dye; and yet fear not Martyrdom for it neither, under the Reign of any Popiſh Succeſſor.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93598:24"/>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93598:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Semper ego Auditor tantum?</hi> OR A VINDICATION OF HIS Royal Highneſs THE Duke of YORK, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ONe might in Charity have thought, That thoſe Peaceable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as they call themſelves, and <hi>Whigs</hi> as every Body elſe calls 'em, after ſo many Defeats as their Seditious Projects, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels of Rebellion have met withal after it was almoſt Viſible, that the particular care of Providence had guarded our Gracious King and the beſt part of his Loyal Subjects, from being Murder'd and Enſlav'd by them, and the Heads of their Faction; for the Deſign was no better. A man might at leaſt have reaſonably imagin'd they would in Policy for a ſeaſon have been Quiet; But they are a Generation of People that no Condeſcention or Indulgence of a Prince can oblige, nor no warning from God, but Plague, Peſtilence, or Famine, reform. For not being content privately to have drawn a horrid Scheme of Seizing, Depoſing, or Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of our Good and Gracious Soveraign, (whom God for ever Protect from their Bloody and Rebellious hands) for the enſlaving every Loyal and true Subject to the Monarchical Government, under the Tyranny of a ſecond <hi>Rump</hi> Parliament, chopt out into ſeveral Committees for the Sequeſtration of Honeſt mens Eſtates into their own Pockets; but now they have the Impudence fairly to tell the World what it was they meant, couching it under the ſpecious Title of a <hi>Tory Plot;</hi> which fooliſh, ſawey, and very dull, though malicious Pamphlet, I the rather think fit in this place to take notice of, becauſe it has ſo much the reſemblance of another call'd, <hi>No Protestant Plot;</hi> That by the deformity and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93598:25"/>
weakneſs of the Ricketty Brats, their old debilitated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather muſt be the ſame.</p>
            <p>And the beſt way of examining that Pamphlet, as I conceive, is to take it as it lyes before us in its Natural confuſion, ſo fairly to work with it in the lump together, ſee what it weighs, and leave it afterwards to the World to judge what it is worth.</p>
            <p>This Pamphlet then in the firſt place is compos'd of about Six Sheets of Paper, fill'd with a morly conceited Preface, and a familiar Treatiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Riſe, Growth, and Diſcovery of a Popiſh Plot; from thence, the Legality, Equity, and Expediency of a Bill of Excluſion; a Curſory and Plauſible Accompt of the Parliaments Proceedings at <hi>Oxford;</hi> a ſawcy Cenſure of His Majeſtie's Declaration after the Diſſolution of that Parliament, and the Addreſſes of the whole Kingdom in Loyal and Duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Thanks for that condeſcending and fatherly Declaration; and to wind up the Bus'neſs at laſt, a ſhort Apology for the Doctrines of Calvin, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with thoſe of <hi>Ignatius Loyola;</hi> a Vindication of St. <hi>Stephen Colledge,</hi> the true Proteſtant Joyner; a Juſtification of the late Treaſonable <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Juries that would not find it ſo, grounded upon that paſs't into an Act in the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and a Proteſtation at the bottom of all, who it is that ſhall not Reign over the mighty, Author of this doughty Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>To proceed therefore with all the Cand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r and fairneſs imaginable, I ſhall in the firſt place enquire how far by his own Arguments he has prov'd the Riſe, Growth, and Diſcovery of a Popiſh Plot, the Legality, Equity, and Expediency of a Bill of Excluſion, how far the Parliaments Proceedings at <hi>Oxford</hi> ſtand by him Juſtify'd, or His Majeſtie's Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and Declaration after it Condemn'd; I ſhall Compare the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of <hi>Calvin</hi> and his Followers, with thoſe of <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> and leave the World to Judge whoſe are the Leſt; then enquire how far St. <hi>Colledge</hi> ought to be Vindicated; the late Treaſonable <hi>Aſſociation</hi> and <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Jury-men juſtify'd in relation to that paſs't into an Act in the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and upon his Proteſtation who ſhall not hereafter Reign over him, make as fair a Concluſion as I can, what ſort of Prince and Government he deſires to be a Subject under.</p>
            <p>This done, I ſhall beg leave to offer ſome reaſonable Conjectures to Publick conſideration, whether or no our Author has, as he calls it, <hi>diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd a Tory Plot,</hi> or has not Poſitively and moſt Learnedly Confirm'd the truth and certainty of a <hi>Whiggiſt Conſpiracy,</hi> carried on for theſe many years together, and couched under the moſt plauſible Pretences of maintaining the Proteſtant Religion, our Property and Privileges, and ſecuring the Subject from Arbitrary Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when upon the whole Matter, nothing has been aim'd at but the Diſſolution of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, the Deſtruction of our Excellent Religion, as now Eſtabliſhed by Law; the rending and ruining of our Properties, and leaving us no Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges at all, and inſtead of ſecuring good Subjects from Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the bringing of us under the moſt odious and inſupportable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93598:25"/>
Tyranny that ever <hi>Athens</hi> knew, or <hi>Rome</hi> groun'd under. 'Tis time now to ſpeak Truth or never; I will do it, and the Devil and Rebels bear the ſhame of it.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place then for his Merry Preface, which I had almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got; He tells us there, that <hi>It is the undoubted Privilege of Parliament, That none ſhould be queſtion'd out of it, for any thing ſpoken or tranſacted in it:</hi> That's falſe: For ſhould any man ſay in Parliament he would <hi>Kill the King,</hi> he ſhall be queſtion'd for it out of it, and I hope Hang'd too; and all, I humbly conceive no breach of Privilege neither: But our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Author to ſhew how fit an Advocate he is for his Party, will needs be at it, and Juggle in his very Preface, which ſhould be his Apology: <hi>None ſhall be questioned out of Parliament, for any thing ſpoken or tranſacted in it!</hi> That is, None ſhall be liable to the Law for what he ſays in Parliament, provided he keep the bounds of Privilege, which I humbly conceive is limited, notwithſtanding the late new ſtarted Doctrines, That they are the only Judges of it themſelves; why elſe do they deſire the Continuation of their Privileges every new Seſſions by their Speaker? The King is the Judge of thoſe Provileges then, for how can any Man grant what is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that is not ſuppos'd the Judge what is ſo? Though therefore none be liable to the Law for what he ſays in Parliament, provided he keep the bounds of Priviledge; yet I hope any Corporation that ſends up a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to Serve for them in Parliament, being ſenſible that that Member has abus'd or not diſcharg'd his Truſt, by proceeding unwarrantably in his Station, running into a faction to do nothing the King deſires of them, to vex him with Bills for Dis-inheriting a deareſt Brother, with a thouſand other Contrivances to perplex the good of the Kingdom, and Embroil ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Settle it: I hope ſuch a Corporation, in an honeſt ſence how they have been miſrepreſented by the Servant, that they have ſent to the King, may have liberty to cenſure the Proceedings of ſuch an unfaithful Servant, and to Vindicate themſelves too by any humble Addreſs to His Majeſty, to aſſert their conſtant and loyal Adherence to his Government; and if need be, Abhorrence of any Tranſactions either of their own Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, or any elſe, that would grow their Maſter, tending to the Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance or Diſſolution of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh, But have a care,</hi> ſays the Preface a little farther, <hi>when His Majeſty ſhall ſay to thoſe dry Bones, Live, and they ſhall ſtand upon their feet, they will be the fitteſt to declare their reſentments,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now do but mark this facetious Gentleman, rather than loſe his Jeſt, what will he not do? Juſt now he was Pleading the reverence and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence due to the Memory of the Parliament, and here he ſcurrilouſly calls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m a Company of <hi>dry Bones,</hi> can there be any thing more Prophane than that! the dry Bones of a dead Carcaſs commonly ſtink in the Noſtrils of the living, a very civil Metaphor. and a great Complement to the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of a Nation truly: <hi>Oh but look to it, they will be fitteſt to declare their reſentments.</hi> I hope it will never come to that, that we of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who ſend up Members to Serve for us in the great Convocation of the Kingdom ſhall ſtand in awe of the Power we truſt 'em withal: I hope
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93598:26"/>
they are to ſit there for our good and our peace, not for our terror: But more of this hereafter. And now</p>
            <p>To the firſt part of his Pamphlet, let us ſee how far he has proved the riſe, growth and diſcovery of a Popiſh Plot: Have at it.</p>
            <p>He ſayes, <hi>If the declaration of the common or publick Judgment be not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent ground for us to ſettle our belief upon, he knowes not what can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be; for if ever the King be infallible, he would the readilieſt expect him to be ſo when he has the concurrent Advice and Conſent of the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Nay he ſayes <hi>there is infinitely greater cauſe for conforming our belief to the Opinion of the King, Lords and Commons in a matter of fact throughly examin'd, then to obey the Lawes they make.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer: That King, Lords and Commons are not nor can be infallible. As they are Men, they are liable to errors, and may be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in matters of Opinion, by the imperfections of their humane Nature in matters of fact, by the falſe Informations of Perjur'd and profligate Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains who are to ſwear for bread, and have no longer hopes to eat, then their Evidence is uſeful: For could any Government or Authority upon Earth be Infallible, one might as well as another, and Conſequently our Author would make a good Argument for the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and the Pope in <hi>Cathedrà</hi> may with as much reaſon pretend to be Infallible, as any Prince in Chriſtendom in his Senate: I hope our Pamphleteer is a better Proteſtant then this Argument amounts to. Granting then that King, Lords and Commons are not Infallible, he has not yet by his argument prov'd the riſe, growth and diſcovery of a Popiſh Plott. But now he comes to ſuppoſing; well, let us ſee what he ſuppoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suppoſing,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>that the aforeſaid Reſolves and Proclamations were not made nor iſſued without the maturest deliberation and fullest aſſurance of the truth of thoſe Testimonies and Evidence that occaſioned them, it cannot be reputed too great credulity to believe that Popery was to be introduced by thoſe Means and Methods that the Diſcoverers of the Plott atteſted:</hi> very good.</p>
            <p>Here he ſuppoſes that the aforeſaid Reſolves and Proclamations were not without the fulleſt aſſurance of the truth of the Evidence: and yet not three lines farther he tells us, that <hi>as to</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>in which the Deſign was laid as well as in</hi> England, <hi>Affairs have been ſo managed, that it is ſtill as to us kept in a great manner ſecret.</hi> Was then that Vote of the Houſe of Commons that there was a Popiſh Plott in <hi>Ireland</hi> as well as here, made upon the matureſt deliberation and fulleſt aſſurance, when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs have been ſo managed that it is yet a Secret? why was this Fellow truſted with Pen and Ink!</p>
            <p>Well, but now look too't, now let us look about us. He has been but tuning his Inſtrument all this while, now he's reſolv'd to tickle it away indeed: as for Example; <hi>Old ſturdy</hi> England <hi>being,</hi> as he ſayes, <hi>a Nation alwayes Jealous of their Rights and Liberties, it was deſpaired, that ſhe would be wheedled to put on the</hi> Roman <hi>Yoke, and therefore there was no hopes of</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93598:26"/>
               <hi>bringing that about but by force</hi> (The Author of this Book muſt be ſome Jeſuited bewhiggify'd and privy to all their Councels, he could never give ſo round an account what they thought elſe.) <hi>And now,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>there wanted a plauſible pretence to get up an Army,</hi> (Politick Worm!) <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> (that we may Epitomize his long-winded Impertinent ſtory) he tells us, <hi>there was a Sham War propos'd with the</hi> French, <hi>and the Parliament in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc't to comply with the deſign;</hi> (he makes a very Worthy Parliament of it the mean while; For if a Sham-War were to be impos'd upon the Nation, he makes the Parliaments as guilty of the Impoſture as any Miniſter of State he would pretend to blacken;) Then he goes on, how <hi>An Army of 30000 men was appointed to be raiſed, and a Tax levied for their Pay.</hi> Well, and they were pay'd as far as the Tax would go, and what harm done?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh but a Peace being Concluded at</hi> Nimeguen, <hi>this Army that was got together by one Seſſions of Parliament, was hardly got diſſolv'd by two;</hi> And all things rightly examined, was not that One Seſſions too ſoon? for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the Disbanding of that Army, 'tis very memorable and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable what Rebellion broke out in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and how it was tim'd; and as for the many Papiſts which he would inſinuate were thruſt into that Army, it is a moſt notorious Lye; for thoſe Papiſts that were in it, were only ſome few Officers that came home upon the King's Proclamation with the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Regiment out of <hi>France;</hi> and they too were caſhier'd their Commands long before the Peace made, or the Disbanding of the Army was thought of; and how this Army, as he ſuggeſts, was probably to be made uſe of in carrying on of the Popiſh Plot, may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd, if I miſtake not, from an Information <hi>Oates</hi> once gave in, That the Officers of it were all to be Murdered in a Night by the Popiſh Party, to render the Army uſeleſs for any Service againſt them. <hi>Then beſides this Open Force,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>there was Listed under-hand a greater, of which</hi> Oates<hi>'s Narrative acquaints us with the chief Officers.</hi> So the Noble Dr. did with Commiſſions too, but the Devil a one was ever yet produced for us to ſee; nor, as I have been told, did the Dr. himſelf know one of theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Officers he has made bold to mention <hi>(viz.</hi> My Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Warder)</hi> when he very lately did ſee him; but that worthy Divine is ſomething apt to be troubled with dimneſs of ſight, when over-ſtrain'd with ſwearing, as ſome Privy Councellors in being can bear him wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>In the next place to his Malicious and Impudent Suggeſtion, <hi>That the ſucceeding Parliament after the Long Parliament, were by their ſudden Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution prevented from bringing thoſe to their Tryals which the Former had committed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, and the whole Kingdom muſt teſtify with me, It is moſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly falſe. For had they ſo intended, they ſate time enough to have brought ſix times the Number to their Tryal. No, the face of things began to look then another way; The Popiſh Plott ſeem'd like a Card turn'd up Trumps, only to be play'd upon a hard Puſh when any Trick they aim'd at was like to be loſt. As for Example; When the King would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93598:27"/>
not give up the E. of <hi>D.</hi> to be torn in pieces, trump with the Popiſh Plot, that will fetch it or nothing immediately; New Dangers of Popery are Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and there is a Young Plot in the Belly of the Old One. But at laſt when that Lord had rendered up himſelf, and deſired a ſpeedy Tryal, diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and perplexities were ſtarted about Joyning Iſſue: then immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there ariſes a ſquobble about Priviledges, An Endleſs confus'd Riddle which no body e're yet could tell the meaning of; but not a grain of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice weigh'd out all this while, but the courſe of it ſtopt, and the Nation kept in ſuſpence, terror and perplexity with almoſt every man's hand at his Neighbours Throat, and all for a punctilio: Juſtice, I doubt, was not what the prevailing Faction at that time Aim'd at: For (as I promiſed before) I will ſpeak Truth, A prevailing and a dangerous Faction were in that Parliament, and will be in every Parliament, 'tis to be feared, ſo long as Schiſmaticks and Make-bates are tolerated in their Inſolencies by Wilful blindneſs or ſcarfulneſs of Magiſtrates that ſhould ſuppreſs them, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to carry ſo great a ſway in Elections, as to return frequently ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Old Rebels againſt the laſt King, to ſit in the Houſe of Commons, only to raile and bandy Factions for the Ruin of this. No, the Popiſh Lords in the <hi>Tower</hi> were to be well husbanded, and that Parliament was Diſſolv'd, not that they ſhould not bring thoſe Lords to Tryal, but becauſe they would not.</p>
            <p>Having ſhot this Bolt, Now he runs on his Story to ſeveral Worthy Peers Petitioning for the Sitting of a Third Parliament: whereof by the way, let us take notice, the E. of <hi>Hunt.</hi> was One, who having ſince diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd the foulneſs of the main deſign at the bottom, has avoided the Infection, return'd home into the Favour and Service of his King, and Safety of his Honour.</p>
            <p>And as that Petition was followed by Others of a more tumultuous nature, ſo the reflections our Author makes upon 'em, are, to deal plainly, as Impertinent as they were: for he ſayes, <hi>That his Majeſty was poſſest by ſome about him, that ſuch Petitioning was tumultuous, and that at the ſame time little Emiſſaries were ordered to diſcourage it; amongst the reſt, Sir</hi> George Jeoffries <hi>here in the City.</hi> Prithee, Brother Pamphletteer, why <hi>little Emiſſaries?</hi> Sir <hi>George Jeoffries</hi> is a Gentleman, and was at that time Recorder of <hi>London,</hi> and, as I conceive, under that character not ſo very unproper to adviſe the City how far in Loyalty, Obedience to the Law and good Manners they ought to preſerve their Duty, Reſpect and Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their Sovereign and his Commands: and for all that quoted ſcrap of the Parliaments Addreſs againſt him, wherein they accuſe him for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the City of <hi>London,</hi> that <hi>ſuch manner of Proceedings might hazard the Forfeiture of their Charter;</hi> I ſuppoſe it had been never the Worſe for that Wiſe City to have taken his Counſel, and have ſav'd perhaps the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which a ſmall Inſtrument, Entituled, <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> lately got amongſt them, may put them to. But it is the way of hireling Scriblers for that Party now-a-dayes to Quote Votes, Reſolves and Addreſſes of the Houſe of Commons for Lawes, forſooth, as if we were no longer to reſpect the Statutes of the Realm for our Guide, but buy a pennyworth of Votes every day, and conſult out of them how far we are to yield Obedience to Edicts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93598:27"/>
of ſo great an Authority as a Kings, who is over us in all Cauſes, next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, the Supreme Head and Governour.</p>
            <p>For he is at the ſame rate again as to the <hi>Anti-Petitions,</hi> as he calls em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or <hi>Abhorrencies,</hi> that were by many of the Loyal part of the Kingdom preſented to his Majeſty in a juſt reſentment and deteſtation of the former Undutiful and Irreverent Proceedings of their fellow Subjects; which as it was at that time the moſt ſeaſonable and honeſteſt courſe that good Subjects could take to clear and ſignalize their Reſpect and Fidelity to a Prince nos'd and affronted by the Inſolent and Vile behaviour of a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and unruly Faction: So I cannot but with Horrour remember the Tyrannical and Oppreſſive Authority which the Houſe of Commons durſt uſurp afterwards over their fellow-Subjects; how many of us were perſecuted by their Ban-dogs and Purſuivants? how many, that knew not ſo well the Charter of their Liberty, were forced to yield obedience to their Unwarrantable and Peremptory Votes, Led in Captivity ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſeveral Miles through their Native Countries up to <hi>London,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Illegal and Chargeable Priſons, harraſs'd with Arbitrary Fines or Cenſures, brought on their Knees, forced to undergo the baſeſt forms of Submiſſion unworthy the honor of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty; and all by an Uſurping Unwarrantable power whom they had never offended, and againſt whom no offence lay! I hope we ſhall feel the ſcourge of ſuch a Tyranny no more.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Author, who after having recited part of an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs made by the Houſe of Commons againſt that Honorable, Wiſe and never to be forgotten Patriot the Earl of <hi>Hallifax</hi> (for the Fellow loves a ſcrap of Parliament bus'neſs better then a dull Pedant ends of Latin) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to <hi>come to the Point,</hi> as he calls it in his Preface, <hi>And now,</hi> ſayes He, <hi>the Parliament according to direction of his Majeſty, Vigorouſly Proſecute the Plot;</hi> That's good News indeed; Let us ſee how: Why he tells us, <hi>Firſt as for themſelves, they by way of Addreſs declare their Reſolution to Preſerve and Support the King's Perſon and Government, and the Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Well, how did they keep their words? Why, the Author gives us to underſtand, that <hi>As to the Plot, they appoint a Committee to take an abſtract of the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of both Houſes as to matters relating to it, upon which they reſolve that the D. of</hi> York<hi>'s being a Papiſt, &amp;c. has given the greateſt Encouragement to the preſent Deſigns and Conſpiracies againſt the King and Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> that is, according to the King's Directions to proſecute the Plot, they reſolve to perſecute his Brother. For methinks it's but an odd way of proceeding, to reſolve any Man is a Papiſt, before they know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or no: at this rate they might have reſolv'd all the City was blown up, though we did ſee one houſe tumble: for the Caſes are paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel; and in ſpight of all Calumnies thrown on that moſt Illuſtrious Prince and Dutifulleſt of Subjects, it was never prov'd that he was reconcil'd to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> yet; nor does the abſenting himſelf from our Church at all evince it: for by that Argument he may be as well a Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter, for ought they know, as any thing elſe. But as to the latter part of their Reſolve, <hi>(viz.) That the preſumption of his being ſo, has given the greateſt Encouragement to the preſent Deſigns againſt the King and Proteſtant</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93598:28"/>
               <hi>Religion.</hi> I agree with 'em: for it is viſible enough 'tis upon that Baſis the Schiſmatick and Phanatical Party have grounded all their hopes of ſpoyling the King of his moſt Eſſential Prerogatives, of deſtroying the whole Beauty and Order of the Eſtabliſhed Church, of collecting together a Treaſonable and Rebellious Aſſociation for fettering up the Power of the King, raiſing an Army to be Commanded by Creatures of their Own, and to obey their Authority for the Enſlaving the Kingdom, rooting out of the Monarchy, and ſetting up Confuſion. Now let all Reaſonable Men obſerve how far our Scribe has proved the Riſe, Growth and Diſcovery of a Popiſh Plot; I will not deny that ſuch a Plot might have been; but for all our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter's arguments, it is at beſt but a Plot preſumptive, and no Plot apparent.</p>
            <p>But upon this Reſolve our Author is pleas'd to remind us of a Bill of Excluſion brought in, which the Lords thought fit to reject; <hi>upon which,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>a Committee of the whole Houſe make two more Reſolves, Firſt, That ſo long as the Papiſts have any Hopes of the D. of</hi> York<hi>'s ſucceeding to the Crown; King, Religion and all are in an apparent danger of being deſtroy'd.</hi> The ſecond, <hi>That the Houſe for Bringing in a Bill of Aſſociation for the King's Defence, and for general Safety, And for preventing the Duke of</hi> York <hi>or any Papiſt from ſucceeding to the Crown,</hi> this is call'd proſecuting the Plot. And here by the way it will not be amiſs in a word or two, to take notice of the latter part of this ſecond Reſolve, <hi>(viz.) Or any Papiſt from ſucceeding to the Crown:</hi> Whence I obſerve, Either this Reſolve was Impertinent, or it was neceſſary: If there were no reaſon after the Excluſion of the Duke to fear any Popiſh Succeſſor, this Reſolve was Impertinent: If it were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, there muſt be reaſon to apprehend ſuch a Succeſſor. Now who could this be! The Prince of <hi>Orange!</hi> Is he a Papiſt? No, but if need be, there may riſe up an Evidence or two to ſwear him one. For it is to be proved by very Unqueſtionable Witneſſes, That Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> once upon a time in great freedom of ſpeech, and arguing very hotly for the Bill of Excluſion, being interrogated, <hi>If that ſhould paſs, Who he thought fit to ſucceed, Whether the P. of</hi> Orange, <hi>or not;</hi> was pleaſed to expreſs him <hi>No; he was a Canary-Bird, he would have no</hi> Orange: <hi>but if the Duke were once Excluded, he had half a Dozen ſheets of Paper to preſent to the Conſideration of the Parliament for ſettling of the Government,</hi> or to that purpoſe. A very pretty Condition we were at that time running into: at this rate his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence need but have ſworn all the Royal Line out of their Pretenſions, and the bus'neſs had been done. Methinks it would not have been Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the Wiſdom of a Parliament, if once they that had taken the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion off from one hinge, to have ſixt it upon another at leaſt, and not have left the Door open for all manner of Confuſion to have been let in upon us at the diſcretion of a ſwearing <hi>Salamancha</hi> Dr. and as many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as he could have pickt up out of Jayles and <hi>Reggary</hi> to have born record with him: And this granted, let us in the next place examine how far our Author hath evinced the Legality, Equity, and Expediency of a Bill of Excluſion.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall do with the ſtricteſt yet moſt ſincere and impartial ſcrutiny that I can: As firſt, Our Author ſayes, <hi>For the Legality of it,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93598:28"/>
               <hi>he could never hear of more then two things oppos'd; The one, That Kings holding their Crowns by right of Primogeniture, it is againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to put by the next Heir.</hi> The other, <hi>That it is againſt the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That I muſt beg the Gentleman's Pardon, if I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in this point believe him; for I am apt to be perſwaded he may have heard that it is againſt the Fundamental Law of the Kingdom, againſt the expreſs Law and Word of God in his Scripture; that it is againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pact or Covenant whereby we live in Peace and Unity with one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, whereby we Originally conſented and mutually obliged our ſelves to that Excellent Form of Government we are Ruled by and Preſerv'd under againſt that Principal and Sacred Rule by which every Man's <hi>Meum &amp; Tuum</hi> is diſtinguiſhed. I am perſwaded our Author may have heard all this; and that it is ſo, I am perſwaded it will not be very difficult to prove neither.</p>
            <p>For that it is againſt the Fundamental Law of the Kingdom, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in that it is againſt the Publick Safety, which I take to be the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Law: and it is againſt the publick Safety, in that it is againſt the very Being of the Government. Now by the <hi>Being of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> I underſtand the Ancient Hereditary Monarchy; and whatſoever tends to the diſſolution of that, is againſt the Being of the Government: any Bill or Act therefore for excluding a next Heir, tends abſolutely to the diſſolution of the Ancient Hereditary Monarchy, in that it puts it in a meer ſtate of Election: for the very Act of Excluding one Heir, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the Election of another. As for example, when an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is paſſed for the diſ-inheriting the Heir of an Entail'd Eſtate, it is not made an Act for the Excluding ſuch or ſuch an Heir; But for cutting off the original Entail: And the paſſing a Law for diſ-inheriting the Heir to the Crown, cannot be made an <hi>Act</hi> of Excluſion; for <hi>Magna Charta</hi> ſayes no Heir ſhall be ſpoil'd of his Inheritance, but it muſt be made an <hi>Act</hi> of Diſſolution and cutting off the Entail of the Crown, the very Law by which the Heir holds his Right of Inheritance; which would be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtructive of the Being of the Government, and conſequently Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Safety: for ſhould an <hi>Act</hi> be made to diſ-inherit the Heir of an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail'd Eſtate without cutting off the original Entail, the <hi>Act</hi> would be void in it ſelf and of no force, becauſe againſt the Fundamental Statute of <hi>Magna Charta:</hi> But the cutting off the Entail removes all manner of Right to Inheritance, and leaves the preſent Poſſeſſor at liberty of chooſing what and how many Heirs he ſhall think fitting. I hope the Ancient Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi> ſhall never be ſo Violated.</p>
            <p>It is alſo againſt the Expreſs Word of God in his Scriptures, which ſayes, ſpeaking of the Law of Inheritances, thus, <hi>If a man dye and have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Numb. Cap. 27. Verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>no Son, then ſhall ye cauſe his Inheritance to paſs unto his Daughter; And if he have no Daughter, then ye ſhall ye give his Inheritance unto his Brethren; And if he have no Brethren, then ye ſhall give his Inheritance unto his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Brethren; And if his Father have no Brethren, then ſhall ye give his Inheritance unto his Kinſman that is next to him of his Family, and he ſhall poſſeſs it, and it ſhall be unto the Children of Iſrael a Statute of Judgment.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93598:29"/>
Can there be any thing more poſitive then this? Here we have the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Command of God for the Lineal Succeſſions of one Heir in default of another down through a whole Generation; nay, He calls it too a <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Judgment,</hi> an unalterable Statute, a Statute upon no conditions to be Violated: and ſurely we are not Wiſer or Juſter then the Almighty Author of both Wiſdom and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Moreover, in another place of ſpeaking the Rights of the Firſt-Born, it is ſaid, that <hi>When it ſhall be that a Father maketh his Sons to inherit that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. Ch. 21. Verſ. 16.</note> 
               <hi>which he hath, that he may not make the Son of the beloved, firſt-born, before the Son of the hated, which is indeed the first-Born: But he ſhall acknowledg the Son of the hated for the firſt-born, by giving him a double portion of all that he hath; for he is the beginning of his ſtrength, the right of the firſt-born is his.</hi> So that however merry our noble Author be pleaſed to make himſelf with the Right of Primogeniture, it was a Sacred Law pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the Oracle of God, and by no ſucceeding Ordinance that ever I read or heard of yet repealed. But let us Examine in the next place thoſe Arguments he produces againſt the Right of Primogeniture.</p>
            <p>He has indeed upon this occaſion proceeded in a moſt extraordinary way of Argumentation, which is by asking of Queſtions; which to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him, I will recapitulate here and anſwer as well as I can by Queſtions too, and leave the Reader to Judge whoſe are moſt reaſonable. As firſt then ſayes he againſt the Right of Primogeniture:</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>In how many Kingdoms has Force and Violence, and the longeſt Sword ſettled an Abſolute Monarchy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Muſt therefore we go together by the Ears to Unſettle this Excellent One?</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How oft has that</hi> York <hi>been ſhak't off, and the Government turn'd into a Free State?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Muſt therefore we Rebel again, as we did about 40 Years ago, to become Slaves to the Tyranny of our fellow-Subjects, and at laſt the Rod of an Uſurper?</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How many different Models of both Monarchies and States are there at this day in the World? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Muſt therefore we never reſt contented with the Beſt of Governments, becauſe there are ſo many Worſe in the World to make choice of?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And yet,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>none of theſe Governments, but are or ought to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to for the Lords ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That therefore it is a Sin to alter or endeavour in any point to Violate ſuch a Government. Now the Alteration of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion would be a great Violation of the Rights of this preſent Ancient and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93598:29"/>
Eſtabliſht Monarchy, conſequently againſt the Conſtitution of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore ſinful, in that it ought to be ſubmitted to for the Lords ſake, as our Author has been pleaſed to remind us. But to our Queſtions again, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What ſhall we ſay of Gods giving the Kingdom of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to</hi> Saul <hi>of the Tribe of</hi> Benjamin <hi>the Youngest of</hi> Jacob<hi>'s Sons, or to</hi> David, <hi>the Youngest of his Fathers Sons, and of the Tribe of</hi> Judah, <hi>while none of</hi> Reuben's <hi>off-ſpring ever ſate upon the Throne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. To which I anſwer: Though God had promiſed <hi>Abraham</hi> to make of him a great Nation, that was not yet accompliſhed at the death of his Grandſon <hi>Jacob,</hi> who was at beſt but as a private man, dyed in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where his Poſterity afterwards remain'd in Captivity, and under that Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage multiply'd to a People till they were led out of it by <hi>Moſes,</hi> who eſtabliſhed them into a Nation, and was their Law-giver: beſides, when <hi>Jacob</hi> dyed and bleſſed his Sons, He upbraided <hi>Reuben</hi> of the Sin he had committed, and told him, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtable as water, thou ſhalt not excell, becauſe thou wentest up to thy Fathers bed, then defiledſt thou it.</hi> Beſides, as I ſaid <note place="margin">Geneſis Ch. 49. 1. 4.</note> before, <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not then a Nation till God brought 'em by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> but when the Miracles were begun for the redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the choſen People from Bondage, then the Lord ſpake unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the Paſſeover was inſtituted; then they began to be a Nation of Men, and Modell'd into Government, Marched and Encamped under the Command of <hi>Moſes,</hi> till they were led through the Red Sea into the Wilderneſs, then they fought with <hi>Amalek</hi> and vanquiſhed: After which <hi>Moſes</hi> hearkning to the advice of <hi>Jethro</hi> his Father-in-Law, Choſe able Men out of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who Judged the People at all ſeaſons; the hard Cauſes they brought unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> but every ſmall matter they Judged themſelves; ſo that <hi>Moſes</hi> was their Supream Judge and Law-giver, till he Led them out of the Plains of <hi>Moab,</hi> to the Top of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> where the Lord ſhewed him all the Land of <hi>Gilead</hi> unto <hi>Dan,</hi> and all <hi>Nepthali</hi> and the Land of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And ſaid unto him, This is the Land which I ſware unto</hi> Abraham, <hi>unto</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſaying, I will give it unto thy ſeed; but</hi> Moſes <hi>was not ſuffered to go over thither, but dyed in the Land of</hi> Moab. <hi>Moſes</hi> thus dead, <hi>Joſhua,</hi> by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, ſucceeded him as Judge over <hi>Iſrael.</hi> After <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s death we read, that they forſook the Lord and ſerved <hi>Baal,</hi> and that the Anger of God was hot againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> nevertheleſs the Lord raiſed up Judges and was with the Judge, and delivered them out of the hands of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; but when the Judge was dead, they returned to Corruption again, till the Lord left them to be proved by the 5. Lords of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and all the <hi>Canaanites, &amp;c.</hi> among whom they dwelt, and who were to prove <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to know whether they would hearken to the Commandments of the Lord; but they did Evil, and were ſold into the hand of the King of <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> whom they ſerved Eight Years: but upon their Cry to God, he raiſed up a Deliverer one <hi>Othneil,</hi> who governed them 40 years; to him ſucceeded <hi>Ehud;</hi> after him was <hi>Shamgar,</hi> till renewing their ſins they again were ſold to <hi>Jabin</hi> King of <hi>Canaan;</hi> delivered afterwards and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Deborah,</hi> under whom they had reſt 40 years: After her God rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93598:30"/>
up <hi>Gideon</hi> or <hi>Jerubbaal,</hi> who delivered them from the <hi>Midianites;</hi> after him his Son <hi>Abimelech</hi> was made by them King. <hi>Abimelech</hi> being dead, there roſe up to defend <hi>Iſrael, Jola;</hi> after him <hi>Jair,</hi> and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner were they governed by Judges till the time of <hi>Samuel;</hi> And he in his age made his Sons Judges over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who walked not in his wayes, but turned aſide after lucre, took Bribes and perverted Judgment, upon which the Elders gathered together, and demanded a King of <hi>Samuel</hi> to govern them like other Nations.</p>
            <p>This King was <hi>Saul,</hi> Choſen by God himſelf: there was the abſolute Command of God for the Anointing him King over <hi>Iſrael;</hi> Neither was there any Succeſſion cut off, for <hi>Reuben</hi> had no right ever of it: and the original of Kingly Power in <hi>Iſrael</hi> by Gods appointment began in <hi>Saul.</hi> So that Kingly Power (as much a jeſt as they make of the matter, appears plainly by this to be originally <hi>Jure Divino.)</hi> Were Power ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the People, <hi>Abimelech</hi>'s race who before was choſen King by the People muſt have ſucceeded, but it did not; and the firſt Succeſſive Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy that ever was Eſtabliſhed in <hi>Iſrael</hi> was <hi>Jure Divino</hi> by God's own Law, and confirmed by Promiſe to <hi>David,</hi> but our Author deſires to know, How came <hi>David</hi> afterwards to Reign? How came the Crown tranſlated from <hi>Benjamin</hi> to <hi>Judah?</hi> Why was it not continued in the Tribe?</p>
            <p>Would our Author give himſelf to read the Scripture ſometimes, he would write honeſter Pamphlets, and ask more pertinent Queſtions, for the Kingdom was never Eſtabliſhed upon <hi>Saul,</hi> for having tranſgreſſed the Commandment of God by a prophane Sacrifice; <hi>Samuel</hi> told him he had done fooliſhly, for he had not kept the Commandment of God, for God would have eſtabliſhed his Kingdom elſe upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> for ever, but that now he had ſought a man after his own heart, which was <hi>David:</hi> So by this it appears, that though <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf was King, the Kingdom was never confirmed or promiſed to his Seed. And therefore the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it to <hi>David</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> is no Argument for the cutting off a Succeſſion eſtabliſhed for ſo many Ages as this Ancient Monarchy of <hi>England</hi> has been. But here's ariſen another Queſtion</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How came</hi> David <hi>to put</hi> Adonijah <hi>by the Throne, and ſeat</hi> Solomon <hi>in it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſnw.</hi> Why, did <hi>Adonijah</hi> Rebel and uſurp the Kingdom from his Father while he was yet alive? Did the Duke of <hi>York</hi> ever Rebel; nay, did he ever murmur againſt the King his Brother? Have not the King's Commands been always Sacred to him? what Dangers has he refus'd? what Exile not choſen when the King gave his Decree for it? though had it been in his Nature, he might like a rebellious <hi>Abſolom,</hi> have ſtood upon terms of Privilege too; but while one choſe rather to be a ſtiff-neck't Duke, than a beloved Son, He choſe rather to be a dutiful Brother than a ſtubborn Subject. Neither was the Right of Succeſſion to the Throne of <hi>David</hi> by any Law ſettled upon the Elder, and beſides the Rebellious Uſurpation of <hi>Adonijah, David</hi> had before ſworn that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould Reign after him,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93598:30"/>
and ſit upon the Throne in his ſtead; ſo that in the firſt place, here was no Entail of Succeſſion violated, though Rebellion (if any thing) might have warranted it. But in our Law ev'n in caſe the Heir to the Crown ſhould Rebel, though he ſhould be attainted of Treaſon to incapacitate him of Succeſſion, this would not do if his Head ſtood upon his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders neither; for the Deſcent of the Crown upon that, cures even an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder. But a Bill of Excluſion is a new-ſangled thing, that never was heard of before, inconſiſtent in it ſelf, tending both in Law and Reaſon to nothing elſe but embroyling us into general Confuſion, and utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminating the very foundation of the Monarchy. Thus far I hope we have ſufficiently overthrown the legality of a Bill of Excluſion; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that no ſuch thing can be paſs'd in Law without taking the whole frame of the Government to pieces, and ſetting up a new one: But the Arguments our Author urges, which ſuch a Bill is not againſt the Oath of Allegiance, and the Conſequences he deduces from them, are indeed very conſiderable. Firſt, He tells 'tis Nonſence to affirm, that any one is a Man's Heir or Succeſſor while himſelf lives. Then I ſay, the Oath of Allegiance is againſt common ſence; and by Sir <hi>F. W</hi>'s Argument in the Houſe againſt Expedients Void therefore in it ſelf, and of no force; for if an Act of Parliament againſt common ſence be in it ſelf Void, certainly any Oath againſt common ſence inſtituted by Act of Parliament is ſo too: But why is it Nonſence to affirm, That any one is a Man's Heir or Succeſſor while himſelf lives! <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Succeſſor Commences ſuch only at his Predeceſſor's Death:</hi> which by the way, ſeems to me much the more Nonſence of the two; for every Succeſſor to the Crown, at the inſtant of his Predeceſſor's Death, <hi>De Jure,</hi> becomes no longer Succeſſor, but very Poſſeſſor, though not confirm'd ſo <hi>De facto</hi> till his Coronation; ſo that to do the Oath of Allegiance Juſtice, it is no Nonſenſical Oath, for all our Author's Nonſenſical Argument; but an Oath that obliges eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true Subject to Adhere to the King and his Lawful Succeſſors, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever go about by any unlawful Act (as we have prov'd one of Excluſion muſt be) to deprive the Duke of <hi>York</hi> of his Right to Succeſſion, does it againſt the Oath of Allegiance, and is no better than perjur'd. But now all the Queſtion is, ſays our Scribler, whether ſuch a particular man has ſo unalterable right to ſuch a ones Heir, that no crime Can forfeit that Right, nor no Power annul it: To which I anſwer, as he himſelf hath taught me; Force and Violence, and the longeſt Sword may annul any thing; but the Buſineſs he would bring in here, is the forfeiting Crime, which what it is in our preſent caſe, we ſhould better have known; He ſays, <hi>If the haſty Diſſolution of ſo many Parliaments,</hi> and a <hi>Noli Proſequi had not hindered;</hi> and ſo he proceeds to make a Fiction of Caſe (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is a Subſtantial Fiction) by his old way of ſuppoſing. Now let us once more ſee what he ſuppoſes; for by this ſuppoſe, he pretends to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Query, what the forfeiting Crime is in our preſent Caſe. Very good, <hi>Suppoſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>him that expects to be Heir, perverted from the Protestant to the Popiſh Religion;</hi> Now out of this Suppoſe, we are if we think fit to ſuppoſe agen, that he means the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and then we are to let him know, 'tis but a malicious at beſt, and no charitable Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and till there are better grounds than any the Publick have been inform'd of yet to ſix it upon, I ſhall grant no ſuch Suppoſition at all, In
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93598:31"/>
the next place, ſays he, <hi>Suppoſe his Principal Servant, and greateſt Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, bragging of the apparent likelihood of rooting out this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtilent Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Hereſie, and of the Zeal of his Maſter in the Cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. Now we are ſure, and need not ſuppoſe that by this Servant and Confident is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd <hi>Coleman;</hi> and therefore I muſt tell, he is pleaſed to ſuppoſe what I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve himſelf and almoſt every body elſe knows to be a falſe thing; for <hi>Coleman</hi> was none of his Principal Servant or Confident, but Caſhier'd the Service of his Highneſs's Family many years ſince; and I have been told, the reaſon why he was diſcharged the Office of Secretary to the Dutcheſs, was for that he ſtood ſuſpected even then of being too buſie with Matters of an ill kind, though they were not particulariz'd or prov'd againſt him; and if ſo, good Mr. <hi>Pamphletteer,</hi> what becomes of your Suppoſe? But to proceed, Suppoſing all this ſays he, <hi>We can hardly imagine a Crime to be blacker.</hi> Then what? <hi>Then a ſuſpition of deſigning the Subverſion of the Eſtabliſhed Religion, and in it of the Government;</hi> A very pretty point our Author has brought his Bus'neſs to: He has proved the Lawfulneſs of the Bill of Excluſion, becauſe he is pleaſed to ſuppoſe, and ſuſpect that the Duke may deſign the Subverſion of the Religion and Government; is any man to ſuffer by the Law of <hi>England</hi> for Suſpition? Surely no: Then certainly the Excluding the Duke from his Inheritance upon bare Suſpition, is not altogether ſo legal as our Author would have the World think it is. But the man is a little reaſonable for all that; for about four Lines afterwards, ſays he, <hi>Now let us conſider,</hi> (introth and I think it is time of all Conſcience) well, but what ſhall we conſider! <hi>Let us conſider,</hi> ſays he, <hi>whether a Parliament have not Power to inflict ſuch a Puniſhment on ſuch Offences:</hi> with all my heart: <hi>It is,</hi> ſays he, <hi>from the Laws Enacted by Parliament, that ſuch an Act has ſuch a Puniſhment awarded to it:</hi> This, as he has expreſs'd it is Nonſenſe, and as he means it is falſe, for no Laws are Enacted by Parliament, all Laws are Enacted by the King in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and though he go on to tell us, that Felonies are by the Law Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by Death, as well as Murder; yet till he ſhow us a Law that any man ſhall be Hanged for Suſpition of Felony or Murder, he ſeems to have conſidered to very little purpoſe, and his Suppoſe is in as bad a condition as e'r it was. 'Tis very well worth any man's obſervation how the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions for this Cauſe manage Matters, they write inceſſantly, but ſuch crude and indigeſted ſtuff comes daily from, as viſibly diſcovers what an unhealthful condition it is in. Now is our Author vomiting up a lump of confus'd Notions for the <hi>Mobile</hi> to lap at, and that is forſooth what a Parliament can do: and firſt indeed he is a little civil, and will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to joyn the King with them, and pray let us ſee to what purpoſe: <hi>They,</hi> ſays he, <hi>can Attaint any man, or take off the Attainder, as they ſee good:</hi> I hope though, good Mr. Author, it muſt be for ſufficient cauſe ſhown that they ſhall proceed to Attaint any Man, or elſe by your leave they violate the Great Charter of <hi>England,</hi> and whatſoever does ſo, is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the Being of the Government, Deſtructive of Publick Safety, Deſtructive of the general Liberty; either let the great Charter be the Rule and Standard our Parliaments are to govern their Votes &amp; Acts by, or let us burn and cancel it for ever: Our Law ſays, It is unalterable, and whoever Votes or Conſents to any thing againſt the tenure and holding of that Charter, I may preſume to ſay is little better than a betrayer of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93598:31"/>
the Publick Good, and an Enemy to the Kingdom: The People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hold their Liberties and Properties by virtue of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can alter it, and whatſoever does ſo, call it an Act of Parliament, or what you pleaſe may be impos'd upon our Obedience by Power, but it is Void of it ſelf, Tyrannical, and againſt the great and Sacred Right de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us down through ſo many Ages, by our Fathers from one Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to another. It would argue as much impertinence as he is guilty of himſelf, to recount the many abſurdities he has urged on this occaſion; as the inſtances of Legitimation and Illegitimation of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> both which were made in their turns Illegitimate, and yet both were Legitimate when they came to ſucceed, and would not any Body that reads this judge our Author deſerved a blew Coat and a Muckinder for urging their Caſes as Inſtances what the Parliament can do in ſuch Caſes, when neither of the Acts paſs'd againſt thoſe Princeſſes ſtood good. But what he ſays afterwards, deſerves Sugar Plumbs or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, now we are beholden to him or never; for he comes to the Point and ſays in a word, <hi>That the two Houſes have an abſolute Dominion over the Lives, Liberties and Eſtates of any Subject in the Kingdom;</hi> why now we ſee what the Gentleman would be at, here he ſpeaks home, <hi>The two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes abſtractedly have an Abſolute Dominion,</hi> &amp;c. Tuſh, no matter for the King, he is no body God knows, when our Author would ſhew his Law: <hi>We have had inſtances</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>of Queens being Beheaded, and who is near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier related to the King than ſhe that is one with him</hi> (Oh brave Boys) <hi>who nearer allied to the Privileges of the Crown than ſhe that has had it ſet upon her head?</hi> Why this is hearty now, <hi>And if ſuch a one</hi> (ſays he further) <hi>may be brought to the Scaffold, and dye the deſerved Death of a Traytor, no man can argue the High Court that condemned her to dye, of Injuſtice.</hi> This is as plain as the Noſe in ones face, it would have coſt Thee but a little more Ink and Paper Friend to have told us we have had an inſtance too of a Bleſſed King brought to the Scaffold, Condemned by a High Court to a High Court of Juſtice, as they call'd themſelves: Thou mightſt have urged this as well as hinted it ſo plauſibly, the Parallel was indeed finely ſpun, we might eaſily ſee what it Tally'd to<hi>:</hi> but thou mighteſt to ſhew the boldneſs of thy Skill have ſteer'd a little nearer the Quickſand, juſt rais'd upon the Surface of it: 'twould have ſhown thee a fit Fellow indeed to Vindicate the Diſheriting an Heir to the Crown, Overthrowing a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and confounding the Safety of thy fellow-Creatures and Subjects. Thus has our Author taken a great deal of pains to overthrow the Right of Primogeniture by Arguments that overthrow themſelves, To juſtifie an Act of Excluſion would be no Violation of our Oath of Allegiance, when it is abſolutely againſt the tenure, expreſs words and meaning of it, asked Queſtions to as little purpoſe as he has rais'd Arguments; and ſo much as he ſays for the Legality of the Fact.</p>
            <p>Now as to the Equity of it, never was any thing more profoundly dull than he: <hi>It is,</hi> ſays he, <hi>an Act of the greatest Equity and Juſtice in the World.</hi> One would think now after ſo Dogmatical a Propoſition he would do us reaſon, and make his words good, and he goes about it very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly truly; for he is at his <hi>If</hi>'s and <hi>Suppoſes</hi> again in a trice: <hi>If</hi> (ſays he) <hi>he that pretends to the Succeſſion be a Perſon that is already engaged in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93598:32"/>
               <hi>to alter the Government, that by the accurſed tye of his deluded Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the deſtructive Principles of his Religion has given certain notice that he thinks himſelf obliged to Extirpate the Religion Eſtabliſht, and to perſecute the reſolv'd Adherers to it to the Death; what in the whole World is more equitable, and moderately Juſt, then that this Perſon ſhould be inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitated from doing all this evil, by preventing his Acceſſion to the Throne, which he will thus Defile with Blood, and Prophane with damnable Hereſie?</hi> Which I anſwer thus: If he that pretends to the Succeſſion be a Perſon that never was engag'd in any Deſign to alter the Government, but has through the whole courſe of his life to this day endeavour'd by the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of his life for the publick Service when ever call'd to it, by the moſt abſolute Obedience and patient Sufferings of the beſt Patriot and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt Subject contributed to Defence and Preſervation of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from ruin, if from the teſtimony of a good and tender Conſcience he has given certain aſſurance that he will ever to his Power maintain the Religion Eſtabliſh't and defend the Adherers to it; (as the Letter from <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> ſufficiently teſtifies the Duke of <hi>York</hi> has done) what in the whole World more unequal or impiouſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, then that this Perſon ſhould be incapacitated from doing all this good, by cutting off his Succeſſion to a Throne, which he may in all likelihood adorn with ſo much Mercy and Honour, with the Defence of the beſt Religion (I mean the Church of <hi>England</hi> as now Eſtabliſh't) in the World. And ſo much for the equity of the Fact.</p>
            <p>And as to the expediency of it, he is driven very hard, for he is forced to quote the Saying, as he is himſelf pleaſed to term it, of a bad Man, <hi>(viz.) It is expedient that one man die for the People.</hi> Where by the way, I cannot but take notice, that to the beſt of my remembrance I have read a Printed Sermon Preached upon this very Text juſt before the Murder of the late King, 'tis an unlucky Obſervation, but our Author muſt Pardon me: and now he ſubjoyns that he would not blaſpheme his Saviour with comparing the Perſon now under conſideration to him, nor would I have the Perſon now under conſideration be Condemn'd by an Injuſtice equal to that us'd againſt our Saviour neither; that is, by the Teſtimonies of falſe Witneſſes, and the Outcrys of a Jewiſh Rabble, when there is no fault found in him: But this Point of Expediency our Author thinks not fit to inſiſt much upon, but refers us with a Complement to the <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> whoſe pretended Author under favour, may in time, as it is humbly ſuppos'd, for that noble Treatiſe, and ſome other freedoms of Speeches he has taken in Taverns, and elſewhere, come to leave his foul Ears upon a Pillory: And now, I think, we have done with the main part of our Pamphlet, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Legality, Equity, and Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of a Bill of Excluſion. I ſhall now proceed to examine what Juſtice our Author has done the Cauſe he eſpouſes, how far the Proceedings of the two laſt Parliaments ſtand by him juſtify'd, or His Majeſtie's Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, and Declaration after it, Condemned. And ſo forward.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt, I have in ſome meaſure ſpoken already, but ſince our Scribler has thought fit to ſtir up the Embers yet farther, I cannot but take notice. And here all the World are deſired to obſerve too with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93598:32"/>
what impudent Falſhood he has recited the Bus'neſs &amp; Caſe of <hi>Fitz-Harris:</hi> Firſt, he ſays of that Libel, <hi>That it was a Sham-Plot contrived in the Name of the Non-Conformiſts, and was to be Printed and ſent about by the Penny Poſt to the Proteſting Lords, and the leading Men of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who were to be taken up as ſoon as they had it, upon hopes that upon ſearch it might be found about 'em:</hi> In anſwer to this, it is impoſſible not to ſpeak the truth; and in ſhort the truth is thus: The Authority and Credit of a Popiſh Plot begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Opinion of all reaſonable, and equally judging men to decline: I mean in the horrid Circumſtances of it, as of Piſtolling, Stabbing, Poiſoning of the King (no body knows which,) and Maſſacring the People: With the credit of this declined likewiſe the Intereſt and Authority of a Faction who had rais'd themſelves at this Conjuncture under the Name of true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants forſooth (caſting by that a ſlight of Corruption upon the Eſtabliſh't Church) to a condition of capitulating for whatſoever their Deſtructive Principles, and deſire of change perſwaded them was for their Advantage, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the overthrow of Monarchy &amp; Epiſcopacy, for ſetting up Presbytery and Anarchy. It appear'd by this, that the credit of the King's Danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſaſſinated by the Papiſts, &amp; the Intereſt of the Republican Faction were Equilibrious, and depended meerly upon the weight of each other; that is to ſay, the Credit of the Plot could not ſubſiſt, but as it was to be fomented by the Authority of the Republican Faction, nor the Authority of that Faction maintain it ſelf, except the credit of the Popiſh Plot were in every of its parts ſupported, this was the Caſe then, and upon this Principle they proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: No ſooner was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Diſcovery of the Popiſh Plot made, by an Inſtrument of their own, a Renegado Deacon, that ſince has uſurpt the Title of Dr. the Offspring of a Notorious Anabaptiſt, and himſelf at this preſent under moſt Vile Suſpitions of wanting the Bleſſed Sacrament of Baptiſm, a Fellow that has renounc'd the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and has ſince been a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Popery it ſelf, and almoſt all the Hereſies in the World beſides; I ſay, no ſooner was this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Diſcovery thus made, but immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renouncing all manner of Obedience to the Laws Eccleſiaſtical or Civil: The Trumpets of Sedition were blown aloud in all Quarters of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by Raſcally, Canting, Whining, Bawling Hypocrites, that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Preachers of the Word, I warrant you: Not an empty Cask could be ſet out for ſweetning at a Tavern Door, but whip it was ſpirited away to ſome adjacent Meeting-Houſe or other to make a Pulpit of; where it vented worſe Sophiſticated Doctrine than ever it had done Wine before: Nothing was heard in thoſe Aſſemblies, but Tribulation, Martyrdom, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and Popery, Popery. Immediately upon this and the Calling of a New Parliament, the Zealous Siſters were tongu'd with Guinneys at Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to keep their Cuckolds true to <hi>The Good Old Cauſe,</hi> and its Intereſt; not an old Rebel or Son of one hardly in any County, but perk't up for a Member, and Preach't in ſome Market-houſe or another, to draw in Knaves and Fools to chuſe him their Repreſentative. As many of this Gang as could be were thus foiſted in, and made Members of the Houſe, whereas it is too apparent they became (to uſe our Author's own terms) <hi>Leading Men</hi> (I cannot ſtifle the Truth, for it will out) Nor is it at all to be wondered, that at the firſt ſtarting of ſuch a Diſcovery, the thoughts of Murdering the beſt, moſt merciful, and juſteſt of Kings; the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the moſt Chriſtian and beſt Diſciplin'd Church in the World; the Subverſion of the equalleſt and beſt conſtituted Government that ever a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93598:33"/>
happy People lived under; it is not, I ſay, to be admir'd that ſuch thoughts as theſe ſhould have very deep Impreſſions upon the Souls of the honeſt loyal Subjects, and true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> as doubtleſs the beſt part of that Parliament were, and therefore more eaſily to be led away, as I doubt not but a great many of them have ſince found themſelves to have been by the ſpecious pretences, how corrupt ſoever the ends were of thoſe <hi>Leading Men:</hi> For Immediately the Game was ſtarted, and all the cry was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, <hi>Ill Miniſters, Arbitrary Council,</hi> and fear of <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> the Army then on foot muſt with all ſpeed be Disbanded, though there never appeared to be more need of one, if all the Dangers that were Sworn and Voted had been true; yet no ſooner was this Army gone, but inſtead of a Popiſh Inſurrection in <hi>England,</hi> we had a <hi>Whiggs</hi> Rebellion in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Swords were once more drawn for <hi>Presbytery</hi> and the <hi>Covenant.</hi> That over, and the <hi>Moors</hi> appearing with a formidable Army before <hi>Tangier,</hi> when a Supply was Demanded for the Preſervation of that Garriſon, the great Security of our <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Trade, none could be granted till Grievances were Redreſſed forſooth; and what was the Redreſſing of thoſe Grievances, but cutting off the Duke of <hi>York</hi> from the Succeſſion; turning out all Officers of Truſt about the King, and putting in ſuch in their Places as the Parliament ſhould approve of, Reforming the <hi>Militia,</hi> and as Sir <hi>W. C.</hi> was telling us plainly if his Mouth had not been ſtopt, the <hi>Fleet</hi> too; and putting both into ſuch hands as a Committee, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be appointed by the <hi>Leading Men</hi> at that time for that purpoſe ſhould have thought fitting, very fine! and this was all called Proſecuting of the Popiſh Plot, though not one, except <hi>Coleman,</hi> was ever brought to Juſtice all this while for the Conſpiracy, but a few tatter'd wandring Prieſts, that were hunted, catcht and Hang'd up to fleſh the Rabble withal: We were fed up and kept in heart indeed by ſtrange Reports of mighty Diſcoveries made by the Committee of Secrecy, who had Power given 'em to Examine Perſons, Papers, and Records, ſat for two years and upwards, brooding over the Bus'neſs till it was boaſted, That if <hi>Oates</hi> and all his Brother Evidences were Dead and Rotten, they had proof e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to Condemn all the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and the reſt of the Papiſts then in Cuſtody for the Plot, though when all came to all, no Lord was brought to his Tryal but the Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> and he too (had not <hi>Turber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> (by what means I ſhall not here enquire) been found out long after for a Witneſs) for ought I perceive by the Printed Tryal, might have had his Head upon his Shoulders to this day: In ſhort, the Popiſh Plot was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heartily Proſecuted by the Parliament. The <hi>Leading Men</hi> at that time ſeem'd to have other bus'neſs; The Evidences a pack of Profligate Fellows rak't out of Goals and Dungeons, boaſted ſome of them they had Plot enough yet to hold theſe Seven years<hi>:</hi> The King inſtead of being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd from the Danger of his Enemies, was only teized with Addreſſes to Paſs an Act for the Diſ-inheriting of his Deareſt Brother, was tugg'd and almoſt every day wreſtled with for ſome Limb of his Prerogative or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and no Money was to be given him for Defraying the neceſſary Charges of the Government till he would conſent to ſuch unreaſonable Demands as the <hi>Leading Men,</hi> I mean, the Faction thought fit at that Conjuncture to make him. And all this was ſtill call'd, <hi>Proſecuting of the Popiſh Plot.</hi> Nay, ſo very high ran this Preſumptuous Tide, that in an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93598:33"/>
Addreſs made by the Commons in Anſwer to the King's Meſſage concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Tangier,</hi> it almoſt came to Threats; for as I remember towards the latter end of that Addreſs, mention was made of <hi>Endangering the very Being of the Monarchy it ſelf;</hi> as who ſhould ſay, <hi>Sir, Give us what we Ask, or in plain terms we'll Rebel.</hi> This was ſtill Proſecuting of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot, till at the laſt, when all their hopes lay in the King's, and they were reſolv'd, but upon their own terms, not to ſupply them, out comes a Paper of Votes, one whereof was, <hi>That whoſoever ſhould offer to raiſe any Money by way of Loan upon the King's Revenues or otherwiſe, ſhould be deemed a Betrayer of the Publick Safety,</hi> and I know not what other furious mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to this purpoſe; as if the King were to be Voted into a worſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than any Subject he has, and not be able to borrow, if any of his Loyal People think fit to lend it him. This, and ſome other Proceedings much of the ſame Nature, awaken'd the ſleepy Underſtandings of a great many, who by the Publick Buz had been charm'd almoſt to a Lethargy, the Popiſh Plot began to appear little better than a ſtalking Horſe for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to poach by<hi>:</hi> The Arbitrary Proceedings of the Houſe of Commons over the Liberties of their Fellow Subjects, grew Intolerable unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, illegal, and burdenſom: Immediately the Miſchiefs hatched in 41 began to be reviv'd in the Mouths and Memories of a great many People, who to this day felt the ſmart of them, and dreaded the like Tyranny and Oppreſſion again, till every day the credit of the Popiſh began more and more to break away, and the Workings of the Faction ſeen through it, ſomething plainly. This too as they are a wary Generation, they themſelves perceived, and therefore thought it high time to new vamp up the decaying Plot, and the Meal Tub Stratagem, which brought in <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> having ſucceeded ſo well, Since a new Evidence was wanting, nothing ſo plauſible as a deſign of the like Nature to introduce Mr. <hi>Fitz-Harris.</hi> Thus then they lay their Heads together, and this is agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The King muſt be Libel'd right or wrong: why! becauſe it is <hi>Ad Populum;</hi> for the vileſt Natures are always beſt taken with Slander and Scandal, and apt to believe the worſt things of thoſe which are above them; ſo the Foundation of the Bus'neſs is laid, <hi>viz.</hi> the Libel; but now to build upon this Foundation, that is, to ſix this Libel upon the Loyal Party, (for by this time the <hi>Guelphs</hi> and the <hi>Gibelines</hi> began to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed) there lay the difficulty, and a difficult Point indeed it prov'd; for when it was brought to that, that Mr. <hi>Fitz-Harris,</hi> who was to be the Diſcoverer, asked his Pardon, His Majeſty was better advis'd than to give it him, except he would deſire it by telling honeſt Truths, which was not in the Gentleman's Inſtructions at that time; ſo he went to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> and the Deſign was all intangled: But when the hopes of the Godly Party was got into <hi>Limbo,</hi> Bleſs us how they buſled! how was he viſited by Sir <hi>R. C.</hi> and Sir <hi>G. T.</hi> to take his Examination as they call'd it; but whether they came to inform themſelves, or him, that's yet a Queſtion; for Matters were carry'd very privately. This worthy Gentleman or Captain being brought to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> towards his Tryal, for you know all our Diſcoverers are or ſhould be Doctors or Captains, as Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> Dr. <hi>Tongue,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lower,</hi> Capt. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> Capt. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> Capt. <hi>Wilkinſon,</hi> and ſo forth; this Captain then, as I ſaid, being brought to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in order to his Tryal, it was juſt like the roaſting of a Cat alive; for as upon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93598:34"/>
that occaſion, all the Cats in the Neighborhood will come and ſquale, briſtle, and ſcratch for the reſcue of their Companion; ſo all the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences were alarm'd here. The Dr. of <hi>Salamancha,</hi> like a great Boar Puſs came in the Van, and roar'd moſt hideouſly, the reſt ran about the place, whether with their tails an end, I know not, ſputtering, wawing and ſpitting too abominably. Then and by theſe his Brethren was put into his hand his Plea, of ſtanding Impeach'd by the Houſe of Commons, and ought not therefore to be try'd by any Inferior Juriſdiction, which Impeachment by this appears in all Moral probability haſtened, as it was by the <hi>Leading Men,</hi> to have been made much rather to obſtruct the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the King, in not permitting a Traitor to be brought to Juſtice, than any thing elſe; a Vote having paſs'd the Lower Houſe, upon the Lords refuſing to receive the ſaid Impeachment, That to try Mr. <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> in any Inferior Court, was a Violation of their Privilege, and againſt the Conſtitution of Parliaments; and this too was Proſecuting of the Popiſh Plot, this was bringing Traytors to Juſtice; upon which let us reaſon a little.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> were Guilty of the higheſt Treaſon in the World, as certainly he was, and by ſuch apparent Proofs, that it was impoſſible he could eſcape Juſtice in any Court in <hi>England,</hi> what need was there at that time for his being Impeached in Parliament who had ſo much bus'neſs already of a higher Nature before them, as the farther Enquiry into the Popiſh Plot, as to which the greateſt part of the Kingdom are yet in the dark, the bringing of thoſe Lords Impeached already to their Tryals who had lay'd ſo long under a cloſe and burdenſom Impriſonment, that it is a ſhame to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty we ſo much boaſt of all over the World? What Neceſſity was there for the Houſe of Commons to engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſuch a Tedious Bus'neſs as a Parliamentary Proceſs muſt be, againſt ſo inconſiderable a Creature as <hi>Fitz-Harris,</hi> who was already a Priſoner by Warrant from the Council, and lookt for every day to be brought to Trial by the ordinary courſe of Juſtice? There muſt be ſomething in this bus'neſs more than ordinary: and what this ſomething was, eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the many Tricks and Circumventions us'd at his Tryal to Impede the Proceedings; as firſt his own Plea, upon the Vote above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, try'd and in Law over-ruled, ſo as it is apparent from thence, that Vote was Illegal and againſt Juſtice: Secondly, the endeavouring to ſave him, by ſetting him up (even at the time that he ſtood Arraigned for the baſeſt Traitor) for a new Evidence. For this we may thank that worthy Grand-Jury, who immediately upon his ſingle Depoſition in thoſe ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Circumſtances, thought fit at a venture to find a Bill of Murder againſt the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> and yet upon the hearing of ſeveral unqueſtionable Witneſſes, one of the ſame ſtamp, reſum'd <hi>Ignoramus</hi> upon <hi>Colledge</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment. From this I ſay it is apparent (whatever the meaning of the bus'neſs was) that the Impeaching this Fellow in Parliament, tended na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally rather to obſtruct the Safety of the King, in not permitting ſuch a Traitor to be brought to the ſpeedieſt Juſtice, than any thing elſe; and by what Hands, what Party the Treaſon he Dy'd for was ſet on foot, is ſufficiently evident from his laſt dying Confeſſion, written by his own Hand, and deliver'd to Dr. <hi>Hawkins</hi> the worthy Miniſter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93598:34"/>
of the <hi>Tower,</hi> and to the ſaid Doctor's farther Relation of it deliver'd to the World in Print, I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>Next as to His Majeſtie's Declaration after Diſſolving of the Parliament, which ſticks ſo much in our Gentleman's Stomack, <hi>Wherein he gave aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that he would call frequent Parliaments,</hi> &amp;c. by our Author's good leave, according to a late diſtinction of a Brother Block-head of his, they are not the many, but the few that long for the performance of the firſt promiſe: The many and beſt part of the People reſt well aſſured of the performance, do not long nor are clamorous for it: They are ſatisfy'd the King may keep his word of uſing frequent Parliaments, without the calling a New one once a Quarter; 'tis convenient as matters go, that the King ſo time his Affairs, as to get a Parliament that will mind his and his Peoples Intereſt, and not be carry'd away by the Factious Deſigns and Intrigues of <hi>Leading Men</hi> any more: I am aſhamed ſo Great and Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Aſſembly as an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Houſe of Commons, ſhould not be ſo Wiſe too as not ſuffer any ſuch Name as a <hi>Leading Man</hi> amongſt 'em: One would Imagine that in ſuch a high Convention choſen out the whole Kingdom, every one ſhould have Wiſdom and Reaſon enough of his own to guide his Opinion by, and not run and Baa like a ſilly Sheep after the Low-Bell of another's Cant. And this ariſes moſt commonly from the chooſing Men to be our Repreſentatives in Parliament, that are hardly of years of Diſcretion to take care of themſelves, ſending Boyes that have not yet worn the School-brand out of their Buttocks, to ſit and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult upon the good of the Nation (allow Things of 18 or 19 to make Speeches in a Senate-Houſe, before they know how to make a Theam, what a Shame is this? Methinks we ought to chooſe for the great Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Kingdom, Men qualify'd with the beſt Brains as well as beſt Eſtates among us; Men of the beſt Underſtanding and Experience, and thoſe too fortify'd with Principles of Honour and Virtue, not giddy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed Boyes unable yet to look after their own Eſtates, and therefore very unfit Guardians of the Properties of their Neighbours, who when they come into the Houſe, for want of Judgment to diſtinguiſh betwixt Good and Evil, hunt with the loudeſt Cry, add to the Noiſe, and by Noiſe carry the Bus'neſs; I mean ſuch Bus'neſs as the <hi>Leading Men</hi> think fit to ſet on foot, and that is commonly Faction: Now by the <hi>Leading Men,</hi> I underſtand either thoſe grey Foxes who are well skill'd in the wayes and Methods that brought on our late Confuſions, and hope by the ſame means for their own private ends to Imbroyl us again; or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Spirits, who (by the ill Example of others that have gain'd their Point by the ſame means) hope by running againſt the King, and broaching Popular Grievances to be bought off by Preferments: Theſe are for the moſt part Practiſing Lawyers, which in Reaſon however Cuſtom has prevail'd, ought no more to be admitted into Parliaments, than Butchers into Juries. For, Can it be reaſonably ſuppoſed thoſe ſhould endeavour the making good Laws in the Parliament Houſe, that are to live by the breaches of 'em in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall?</hi> No, they will be ſure not to work ſtrong in one place for fear of ſpoiling their Trading in another; I would indeed have good Lawyers, that is, Men who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Conſtitution of the Government, ſit in the Houſe with all my
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93598:35"/>
heart, but methinks, they ſhould be ſuch as had left off the Practice of Law, were to preſerve the Eſtates they had already gotten by compil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſound Laws, and not ſuch as were to raiſe themſelves Fortunes by by picking flawes in brittle ones.</p>
            <p>For my part ſo long as I live, I will never give my Voice for the Election of a Practiſing Lawyer, for it is to the ſway with ſuch and their Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices who aim at Diſorder have born in the late Parliaments, that we owe for the moſt part our preſent Differences and Diſtempers: upon the curſed hopes whereof was raiſed that never to be forgotten miſchief which threatned us, I mean, a Treaſonable <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> the form of which was lately found in the E. of <hi>Sh.</hi> Cloſet, and of which almoſt the whole Kingdom have Loyally profeſt their Deteſtation and Abhorrence.</p>
            <p>As for the cenſure our ſilly Pamphletteer has paſs'd upon thoſe Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrers, I think it not worth the waſting of Ink and Paper to remark up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, he having been only very dully Pert upon the occaſion, recited part of a great many honeſt Addreſſes, and rail'd moſt fooliſhly upon the Tenure of them, to as much purpoſe, as if one ſhould expoſe the beautifulleſt Picture in the World, and ask the Company if they ever ſaw any thing ſo ugly? would not that be a notable Jeſt? Juſt ſuch a merry Monſter is our Author.</p>
            <p>But as to his qualifying of this above-mentioned horrid <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> by comparing it to that Paſs't into an Act in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it is ſo obvious, ſo notorious a piece of Falſhood, that it would be a Jeſt to go about to confute it, his being much troubled any one ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Doctrine before <hi>Calvin</hi>'s, I think indeed reaſonable; for they are ſo very much alike, they ought never to be diſtinguiſh't. But having overthrown the Bulk of his Pamphlet, I think it not worth my while to rake in the Rubbiſh, but beg leave to make one concluding Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To what end was there ſuch ſtriving and ſtruggling to get the Bill of Excluſion? Is there ſo very great a diſproportion in the Age of the King and his Brother, that His Majeſty muſt neceſſarily dye firſt? I think, and I hope not: Methinks there ariſes in Mora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Conjecture a very ill-natur'd Conſequence upon this, that is to ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The eager purſuit of a Bill of Excluſion, looks not ſo honeſtly as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was pretended to be done. For conſidering a Vote once Paſs'd th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Houſe, <hi>That if His Majeſty ſhall come by any Violent Death,</hi> which Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forbid, <hi>they will revenge it to the utmoſt upon the Papiſt.</hi> Methinks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> looks as if the Bill had been Paſs'd, His Majeſty might eaſily ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been taken off, and the whole Deſign turned upon the Unfortuna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Duke, which the Multitude would eaſily have ſwallowed in Suppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition of his being a Papiſt, and he too that way, have been made Sacrifice to the general fury in this broyl; what Government, what Uſurpation might not have been broacht? And this I obſerve one of the probable Effects that might have followed a Bill for his Excluſion. Secondly, That whereas we have heretofore been Alarum'd with migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Noiſes of <hi>French</hi> Penſioners. I think it would be very ſeaſonable (conſidering the late vaſt Returns of Money from <hi>France)</hi> to enquire
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93598:35"/>
who thoſe <hi>French</hi> Penſioners have been or are; whether ſuch as have fomented our Differences at home, which is certainly the Intereſt of our Enemies abroad; or thoſe that have endeavoured to Preſerve the Government and Kingdom in Peace and Tranquillity; whether the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty who in all their Intelligences and Pamphlets, are now courting the <hi>French</hi> King for a hopeful true Proteſtant one, likelieſt to adhere to him when ever he thinks fit to caſt an Eye this way; or thoſe who would once have made War upon him, and obſtructed the Growth of his formidable greatneſs, could Money have been granted for maintaining the Honour and Charges of ſuch a War; but this is a Point will moſt properly be enquired into, when the Natural Hiſtory of our preſent Diviſions ſhall come to be Written, and then too we may give perhaps a gueſs at what ſort of Prince or Government this our Author and his Party deſire to be Subjects under; whether or no it be our Preſent, Good, Gracious, Merciful, Juſt, Long-ſuffering King, whom Heaven in its Mercy for ever Preſerve from the Curſed Bloody Hands of Hypocrites his Enemies.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
